<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A suddain flash timely discovering, some reasons wherefore, the stile of Protector, should not be deserted by these nations, with some other things, by them very considerable. It was first made visible, the fourth day, after the author heard it reported, that the Lord Protector, had waved the title of King. / By Britans remembrancer.</title>
            <author>Wither, George, 1588-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96775</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3195</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1584_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204088</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863790</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863790</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116005</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96775)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116005)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 200:E1584[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A suddain flash timely discovering, some reasons wherefore, the stile of Protector, should not be deserted by these nations, with some other things, by them very considerable. It was first made visible, the fourth day, after the author heard it reported, that the Lord Protector, had waved the title of King. / By Britans remembrancer.</title>
                  <author>Wither, George, 1588-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 70, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J.S. in little Britain, and are to be sold there, and at the Pile of Bibles, in the corner shop of the east end of the Fish-market in the Stocks; looking into Lumbard street;,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Britans remembrancer = George Wither.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>With a final advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber [i.e. October] 7".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116005:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Suddain Flaſh Timely Diſcovering, Some Reaſons wherefore, the ſtile of <hi>PROTEC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TOR,</hi> ſhould not be deſerted by theſe <hi>NATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONS,</hi> with ſome other things, by them very conſiderable. It was firſt made viſible, The fourth day, after the <hi>Author</hi> heard it repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that the Lord <hi>Protector,</hi> had waved the Title of KING.</p>
            <p>By BRITANS REMEMBRANCER.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—<hi>Poetis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Quidlibet audendum, ſemper fuit, eſtque Poteſtas.</l>
            </q>
            <p>A <hi>Preoccupation,</hi> relating to this <hi>Title.</hi>
            </p>
            <l>If ſome ſhall think, this <hi>Book</hi> miſ-nam'd hath been,</l>
            <l>Becauſe, ſo <hi>long a Flaſh</hi> was never ſeen;</l>
            <l>Know; that, through <hi>Cranies</hi> it did thither fly,</l>
            <l>Where <hi>Touchwood,</hi> and where ſmoking <hi>Flax</hi> did ly,</l>
            <l>Which kindling, made it longer then intended;</l>
            <l>And, was a <hi>chance,</hi> that cannot now be mended.</l>
            <l>But, <hi>Flaſhie Names,</hi> and <hi>things,</hi> thoſe times beſeem</l>
            <l>Which, do not <hi>ſolid-ſerious things</hi> eſteem.</l>
            <l>And, they who are not pleas'd to run a Courſe,</l>
            <l>On <hi>Pegaſus,</hi> may, like a <hi>Hobby-horſe.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J.S.</hi> in <hi>little Britain,</hi> and are to be ſold <hi>there,</hi> and at the <hi>Pile of Bibles,</hi> the corner ſhop of the Eaſt end of the <hi>Fiſh-market</hi> in the <hi>Stocks,</hi> looking into <hi>Lumbard</hi> ſtreet; 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:116005:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116005:2"/>
            <head>To his Highneſſe, the Lord <hi>PROTECTOR.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>SIR, though this <hi>Poem</hi>'s Title, fitted be</l>
               <l>To what I hear, the <hi>World</hi> expects from me</l>
               <l>Upon this <hi>Subject;</hi> yet, a <hi>ſeriouſneſſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It hath, and ſhall no <hi>Flaſhie-things</hi> expreſſe;</l>
               <l>For, tis a <hi>Flaſh</hi> of <hi>light,</hi> as well as <hi>Fire,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which, may give ſight of ſomthing you deſire,</l>
               <l>And ſuch, as will no way diſparage you,</l>
               <l>To give them, either <hi>hearing,</hi> or, a <hi>veiw.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Betwixt your <hi>Highneſs</hi> and the <hi>Parlament,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I, purpoſe not to cheriſh that <hi>Diſſent,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which lately was begun; nor do intend</l>
               <l>That, which may juſtly <hi>you,</hi> or <hi>them,</hi> offend;</l>
               <l>But rather, to unite you ſo together,</l>
               <l>That, Diſadvantage, may befall to neither</l>
               <l>By what, your <hi>Adverſaries</hi> hope to finde</l>
               <l>Effected; (if, you have a <hi>changing minde</hi>)</l>
               <l>And, upon hope whereof, they did prepare</l>
               <l>To act, according as reſolv'd you were.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I am not for my ſelf, yet, grown ſo wiſe</l>
               <l>That, when at hazzard, <hi>Publick ſafety</hi> lies,</l>
               <l>I can be ſilent; though I both diſeaſe</l>
               <l>My <hi>ſelf;</hi> and others, oftentimes, diſpleaſe,</l>
               <l>By my <hi>expreſſions,</hi> who, have <hi>pow'r</hi> and <hi>will,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To miſchieve me, who, purpoſe them no ill:</l>
               <l>For, though a well approved <hi>Author</hi> ſayes,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To pleaſe great men, it merits not leaſt praiſe;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I think, he merits more, who ſpeaks in <hi>ſeaſon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Truths,</hi> warranted by <hi>conſcionable Reaſon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Although on him, a <hi>Prince's</hi> wrath it brings)</l>
               <l>Then, if he flatter'd <hi>Parlaments</hi> and <hi>Kings.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In that reſpect, I judg'd it not amiſſe,</l>
               <l>Unto your <hi>ear,</hi> or <hi>eye,</hi> to offer this,</l>
               <l>A few weeks paſt: But, things did intervene</l>
               <l>That ſeem's of more concernment to have been;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:116005:3"/>
               <l>And kept it off, untill nigh out of date,</l>
               <l>It was become; and came almoſt too late.</l>
               <l>Yet, ſince good uſe may thereof ſtill be made,</l>
               <l>And ſome advantage alſo, thereby had;</l>
               <l>It, now comes forth, that, witneſſe it might bear</l>
               <l>To that, which now, <hi>reſolv'd</hi> on, doth appeare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For, though we know there is in every thing,</l>
               <l>But one <hi>Eſſential Truth;</hi> yet, thence may ſpring</l>
               <l>Such various <hi>Illuſtrations,</hi> as perchance,</l>
               <l>The certainty thereof, may much advance,</l>
               <l>When it appears, they, did the ſame <hi>Truths</hi> own,</l>
               <l>Whoſe <hi>judgments,</hi> to each other were unknown:</l>
               <l>For, when there is thereof no <hi>mediation</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But, as their <hi>ſpirits</hi> have communication,</l>
               <l>It doth aſſure, it flow'd from <hi>Providence,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And, not from any <hi>carnal influence.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Your eye, ſees much: and yet it cannot ſee</l>
               <l>It ſelf, or, what the colours of it be,</l>
               <l>Save by <hi>inferiour things;</hi> and, through inſpections</l>
               <l>Acquired, by the <hi>medium,</hi> of reflexions</l>
               <l>From <hi>ſight-leſs objects;</hi> through which; you may lear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Thoſe <hi>truths,</hi> which they themſelves, do not diſcern:</l>
               <l>And, ſuch like <hi>Objects,</hi> peradventure, He</l>
               <l>Who offers this and theſe his <hi>offers</hi> be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>SIR, therefore now<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be pleaſ'd, one houre, to hear</l>
               <l>What, by my <hi>Muſe,</hi> is fitted for your ear,</l>
               <l>And was prepar'd long ſince, to be preſented</l>
               <l>(Though accidentally, till now prevented)</l>
               <l>And, if it be not ſuch, as, then, will ſeem</l>
               <l>To merit, ſome part, of your <hi>good eſteem,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And, uſefull to preſerve, and to increaſe</l>
               <l>Your <hi>Honour, ſafety,</hi> and the <hi>Common-peace;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Return it, with an <hi>Ignominious Daſh,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And, let it then, (in ſcorn) be call'd, a <hi>Flaſh.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Britans Remembrancer.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:116005:3"/>
            <head>A Suddain Flaſh</head>
            <head type="sub">Made viſible, the fourth day after his <hi>Highneſſe</hi> the <hi>Lord Protector</hi> had firſt waved the Title of <hi>KING.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="prologue">
               <head>A <hi>Prologue,</hi> to him, who ſhall <hi>behold,</hi> or <hi>hear,</hi> this <hi>Flaſh.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>A <hi>Flaſh,</hi> I term this; and 'tis like enough</l>
               <l>That, many men, will call it ſo, in <hi>Scoff;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But, I have got before them; and have, too,</l>
               <l>Some <hi>Reaſon,</hi> wherefore I have call'd it ſo:</l>
               <l>For, to, mine ears, when firſt that <hi>news</hi> was brought,</l>
               <l>A thouſand thoughts, <hi>Fluſht</hi> in, and this <hi>Flaſht</hi> out;</l>
               <l>Which, I have, now, thus <hi>Paper'd</hi> up, for thee,</l>
               <l>To bring to minde what <hi>is,</hi> and what <hi>may be.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Although it ſpeaks in <hi>Rimes,</hi> it <hi>Rimes</hi> with <hi>Reaſon;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And comes in <hi>Haſt,</hi> that it may come in <hi>Seaſon.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If thou regard it, <hi>ſo.</hi> If not: my <hi>Coſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is <hi>Paper, Inck,</hi> and part of <hi>three dayes</hi> loſt.</l>
               <l>Thine may be more; For, much affraid I am,</l>
               <l>That, thou, who ſaw'ſt this <hi>Flaſh,</hi> wilt ſee a <hi>Flame,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs an intervening <hi>Providence</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Prevents, what likely ſeems, to give <hi>Offence</hi>)</l>
               <l>Which, here will <hi>burn,</hi> as well as give a <hi>light,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Till it hath <hi>purg'd us,</hi> or, conſum'd us, quite.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Flaſh.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MY <hi>Muſe,</hi> hath on a ſuddain, once again,</l>
                  <l>Invited me, to this <hi>unuſual ſtrain;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, as the ſtate of my <hi>Affairs,</hi> now ſtands,</l>
                  <l>Hath put upon me <hi>Dangerous Commands:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:116005:4"/>
                  <l>But, I, who muſt obey <hi>Her</hi> when ſhe calls,</l>
                  <l>(What ever hazzard, on my <hi>ſelf</hi> befalls)</l>
                  <l>Submitted to expreſſe, what I ſhould finde</l>
                  <l>Infuſed by her pow'r, in to my <hi>mind;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, hearing that his <hi>Highneſſe,</hi> had deny'd</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Kingſhip,</hi> thereupon, thus <hi>verſifi'd:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, <hi>Poets</hi> (priviledg'd, as <hi>Prophets</hi> were)</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Inſpirations</hi> freely may declare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, hath he wav'd that <hi>Title?</hi> and, I pray,</l>
                  <l>Are you aright inform'd of what you ſay?</l>
                  <l>Did not a <hi>falſe-report,</hi> your ears abuſe?</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Crown!</hi> a <hi>Triple-Crown</hi> doth he refuſe?</l>
                  <l>And will not he, as <hi>Biſhops</hi> us'd to do,</l>
                  <l>Say, <hi>No,</hi> and <hi>take it,</hi> as compell'd thereto?</l>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Miracle of men?</hi> doth he deny</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Kingſhip! freely offered!</hi> which, to <hi>Buy</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So many thouſand <hi>Princes,</hi> have made ſale</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Fame, Faith, Conſcience, Body, Soul,</hi> and all?</l>
                  <l>If this (as you affirm it is) be true;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Friends;</hi> bid henceforth, your <hi>jealouſies</hi> adue:</l>
                  <l>And, let him who miſtruſts him any more;</l>
                  <l>Suſpect his <hi>Honeſt wife,</hi> to be a Whore,</l>
                  <l>And in his breſt, the torments thereof cheriſh</l>
                  <l>Till he repent that <hi>injury,</hi> or <hi>periſh.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, ſince I know what many do ſurmize,</l>
                  <l>(And, what <hi>objections</hi> malice doth deviſe)</l>
                  <l>Let me a little more <hi>expoſtulate;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is it not (think you,) done to palliate</l>
                  <l>The <hi>ſouldiers</hi> humor? or, a <hi>Trick of State</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To draw on ſome thing more, yet aimed at?</l>
                  <l>Is it not by <hi>Deſign,</hi> to bring about</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Advantages,</hi> by overſight left out?</l>
                  <l>Or to delay, a while, what he intends,</l>
                  <l>To feel the <hi>Peoples pulſe?</hi> or for ſuch ends?</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:116005:4"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>No doubtleſſe: Then, make anſwer but to <hi>Three</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Short <hi>Queſtions</hi> more, and they the laſt ſhall be.</l>
                  <l>Expects he not, when <hi>twenty dayes,</hi> are paſt,</l>
                  <l>It ſhould be, <hi>Nolens volens,</hi> on him caſt?</l>
                  <l>Nor is it ſo; for, by that <hi>Inſtrument,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which doth yet regulate this <hi>Government,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No <hi>Law</hi> thereto <hi>repugnant,</hi> can be made</l>
                  <l>Whereto, his free <hi>aſſent,</hi> ſhall not be had:</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>Really,</hi> refuſall he doth make,</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Chriſtian prudence,</hi> and for <hi>Conſcience ſake;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, he may give no cauſe of thoſe <hi>Offences,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Suſpitions, Scandals,</hi> and ill <hi>conſequences,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which may enſue; And, whereof, <hi>Honeſt men</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are much affrayd: Why, did he ſuffer, then,</l>
                  <l>So long time in <hi>Debatings,</hi> to be ſpent,</l>
                  <l>(Since he at firſt diſcovered what was meant)</l>
                  <l>And, did not interdict them to proceed?</l>
                  <l>That, had been a <hi>diſhonourable deed:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, in ſo doing, he ſhould have prejudg'd,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Parlament;</hi> them, <hi>diſimpriviledg'd;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, thereby, ſome <hi>Experiments,</hi> have loſt,</l>
                  <l>Which are more worth, than twice the time they coſt.</l>
                  <l>Beſide, the <hi>matter</hi> is of too much weight,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Each way,</hi> to paſſe, till ballanced aright;</l>
                  <l>And, you have heard it ſaid, what thoſe men are</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who Judge a Cauſe, before the ſame they hear.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus far tis well: But, will he not at laſt</l>
                  <l>When ſome few more, fit <hi>Complements</hi> are paſt,</l>
                  <l>Accept what's <hi>offer'd?</hi> what he did, is known:</l>
                  <l>But, what he will do, cannot be foreſhown:</l>
                  <l>And, we ſhall wrong <hi>Him</hi> (as he ſhould the <hi>State</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Have injur'd) if, we him prejudicate.</l>
                  <l>We may conjecture: And, if I may give</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Judgement,</hi> by the <hi>Symptoms</hi> I perceive,</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:116005:5"/>
                  <l>He never will accept it, till, he ſhall</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> be convinc'd in all</l>
                  <l>And ev'ry <hi>Scruple,</hi> which, this day, offends</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Conſcience;</hi> or disſatisfies his <hi>Friends:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Beyond which, he, that ought would move him to,</l>
                  <l>Doth, what no wiſe, or <hi>honeſt man,</hi> ſhould do;</l>
                  <l>And, would not care, though he were quite deſtroy'd</l>
                  <l>So, his own <hi>Luſt,</hi> and <hi>Will,</hi> might be enjoy'd.</l>
                  <l>If ſo, then, me he hath not, yet, deceiv'd</l>
                  <l>In any thing, which I of him believ'd</l>
                  <l>Since firſt I heeded, by what <hi>Point</hi> he ſteers;</l>
                  <l>(What <hi>Rock</hi> on this <hi>hand,</hi> what on <hi>that,</hi> appears;)</l>
                  <l>What moſt men are, with whom he hath to do;</l>
                  <l>And, why, few know, <hi>which way,</hi> he means to go.</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Foes,</hi> though with his <hi>Bullocks</hi> they have plow'd,</l>
                  <l>Have got nought thereby, whereof to be proud.</l>
                  <l>And, as I live, I, am <hi>thereof,</hi> as glad,</l>
                  <l>As, <hi>therefore,</hi> many others will be ſad;</l>
                  <l>And, if I were (as I have been) a <hi>Boy</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I ſhould make <hi>Squibs,</hi> and <hi>Bonefires,</hi> now for joy,</l>
                  <l>As many would have done, had he compli'd</l>
                  <l>With their deſires, whoſe <hi>Offer</hi> is deni'd.</l>
                  <l>For, in his condiſcending to be <hi>King,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He could have been, at beſt, no <hi>greater thing</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Than other <hi>Earthly Princes:</hi> But, hereby</l>
                  <l>He may aſcend unto a <hi>Soveraignty,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which raiſeth him, nine <hi>Orbes</hi> above their <hi>Sphear,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To be inthroned, where <hi>Immortals</hi> are:</l>
                  <l>And, me, it hopefull makes, to ſee that <hi>Age,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, <hi>Britains genius,</hi> did, long ſince, preſage</l>
                  <l>In that <hi>Prediction,</hi> wherein, was among</l>
                  <l>Some other things, this following <hi>diſtick</hi> ſung:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A King, ſhall willingly himſelf unking,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And thereby grow farr greater than before.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:116005:5"/>
                  <l>For, now, fulfilled ſeemeth, in effect,</l>
                  <l>What, that <hi>vaticination</hi> did predict;</l>
                  <l>Although there ſhould a <hi>Power</hi> elſwhere reſide</l>
                  <l>To bring to paſſe, what is by him <hi>deni'd.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Victorious <hi>Cromwell!</hi> thou, haſt, herein, gone</l>
                  <l>Beyond thy <hi>ſelf;</hi> and ſuch an <hi>Act</hi> haſt done,</l>
                  <l>As few or none, in this, or forraign <hi>Climes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Have equalled, in any <hi>former times.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>ſelf-denial</hi> like this, none, but <hi>He</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Could teach, who, that he might our <hi>pattern</hi> be,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Thrones</hi> &amp; <hi>kingdoms</hi> of this world did ſlight,</l>
                  <l>When he was born up thither, where, he might</l>
                  <l>(And did) behold them, ſpreading forth to view</l>
                  <l>All their <hi>Inchanting pleaſures,</hi> falſe or true:</l>
                  <l>And from him onely, could that <hi>grace</hi> proceed,</l>
                  <l>Whereby, thou doſt perform ſo brave a <hi>deed.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou often haſt deſerved <hi>Mural-Crowns,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For taking <hi>Caſtles,</hi> with high <hi>walled Towns,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And making in ſubjection, to thy powers,</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Cities,</hi> fortifi'd with <hi>Walls</hi> and <hi>Towers:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To thee, for brave Achivements on the <hi>Maine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The chief of <hi>Navall Trophies,</hi> doth pertain:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Triumphant Laurell,</hi> to adorn thy brows,</l>
                  <l>To thee is due, for giving ovethrows</l>
                  <l>To dreadfull <hi>Armies,</hi> that, had elſe inſlav'd</l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>Country;</hi> which, God, by thy <hi>ſword</hi> hath ſavd.</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt ſubdued <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> and great <hi>Kings;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whereby, their <hi>Crowns,</hi> their <hi>Scepters</hi> &amp; all things</l>
                  <l>Belonging to ſuch <hi>Conquerors,</hi> are thine,</l>
                  <l>As truly, as the Clothes I wear, are mine.</l>
                  <l>Yet, theſe are ſlight, and petty <hi>Foes</hi> compar'd</l>
                  <l>To ſome, with whom, thou ſecretly haſt <hi>warr'd:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, for thoſe <hi>Conqueſts,</hi> thou I hope, doſt carry</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Tablet,</hi> with a ſecret <hi>Honorary;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:116005:6"/>
                  <l>Whereby thy vertues fully be rewarded,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Trophies,</hi> of moſt worth, though leſt regarded.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theſe wayes,</hi> thou wert <hi>Victorious</hi> heretofore;</l>
                  <l>And, I will mention one great <hi>Conqueſt</hi> more.</l>
                  <l>By few obſerved: Thou haſt ſtood the Shock</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>malice</hi> and <hi>detraction,</hi> like a <hi>Rock,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>On which the waves and billows of the <hi>Main,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Have ſpent their ſtrength, and foam'd out rage in vain.</l>
                  <l>I, very often, have obſerv'd the fell,</l>
                  <l>Feirce, raging, and <hi>three headed dog of Hell,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With his <hi>three double rows of teeth,</hi> aſſay</l>
                  <l>To tear thine <hi>honour,</hi> and thy <hi>pow'r,</hi> away;</l>
                  <l>With his foule <hi>tongues,</hi> beſpattering thy <hi>fame,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To turn thy <hi>blooming honour</hi> into <hi>ſhame;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I've ſeen this <hi>Cur</hi> oft, dog thee in the <hi>dark,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In hope to <hi>bite</hi> thee, when he durſt not <hi>bark;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, I have heeded, by what ſacred <hi>Charms,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou haſt been hitherto, preſerv'd from harms.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This <hi>Helhound,</hi> thou haſt tam'd without ſo much</l>
                  <l>As giving him a <hi>cruſt,</hi> a <hi>ſpurn,</hi> or <hi>touch;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Meerly by <hi>meekneſs,</hi> and, as <hi>paſſing by</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With diſregard of <hi>cauſleſſe injury;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, now he ſometimes <hi>fawns</hi> on <hi>thee</hi> and <hi>thoſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who are thy <hi>friends;</hi> and, ſnarleth at thy <hi>foes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As if he were appeas'd: which, I believe</l>
                  <l>Is but a cunning <hi>dog trick,</hi> to deceive.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And, yet, among thoſe <hi>victories,</hi> which lye</l>
                  <l>Moſt viſible unto the <hi>vulger eye,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This, thy laſt <hi>conqueſt,</hi> merits admiration</l>
                  <l>Beyond the reſt; And, with <hi>perſeveration</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If thou maintain the ſame, as thou maiſt do,</l>
                  <l>By his help, who hath aided hitherto,</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt thereby a <hi>pledge,</hi> that, <hi>God</hi> will never</l>
                  <l>Forſake thee; but, thy <hi>guardian</hi> be for ever.</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:116005:6"/>
                  <l>Thou haſt already ſcap'd, the <hi>beſt tride ſnare;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That <hi>Sathan,</hi> or his <hi>agents,</hi> can prepare:</l>
                  <l>For, 'twas the laſt, of thoſe <hi>temptations,</hi> which</l>
                  <l>He practiſ'd by, our <hi>Saviour,</hi> to bewitch:</l>
                  <l>And, as when that <hi>grand-tryall,</hi> had an end</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Angels,</hi> did forthwith, on him attend</l>
                  <l>Rejoycing in his <hi>conquest;</hi> ſo, will, too,</l>
                  <l>For thine, all, thy moſt faithfull <hi>ſervants</hi> do.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou haſt thereby, ſo ſtrengthned all their <hi>hands,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So cheered all their <hi>hearts,</hi> throughout theſe lands,</l>
                  <l>Who <hi>prayd,</hi> or <hi>feared</hi> for thee, in this tryall;</l>
                  <l>That, thou, of nothing now, canſt have deniall,</l>
                  <l>Wherein their love may ſerve thee; and they ſhall</l>
                  <l>More <hi>fortifie</hi> thee, than a <hi>Brazen wall;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>More <hi>comfort</hi> thee, than ought that can be had</l>
                  <l>From any <hi>Title,</hi> that the <hi>world</hi> ſhall add:</l>
                  <l>And, thou at laſt, ſhalt finde, thou doſt not loſe</l>
                  <l>One <hi>grain,</hi> of what thou lately didſt refuſe,</l>
                  <l>By that <hi>refuſall:</hi> for, thou ſhalt have more</l>
                  <l>(If not in <hi>kind</hi>) in value, than before.</l>
                  <l>Yea, peradventure, that, in <hi>ſpecie,</hi> too,</l>
                  <l>When, qualified, no offence to do;</l>
                  <l>And, when it hath been prov'd, whereto thy <hi>mind</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVithout <hi>diſſimulation</hi> is inclin'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, tis not meer <hi>negation</hi> of that <hi>title,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich is thy <hi>Teſt;</hi> ſince, that availeth little</l>
                  <l>One way or other, ſave as unto that</l>
                  <l>VVhich brought it hath unto diſlike of late;</l>
                  <l>Or, as it may concern ſome <hi>paſt tranſactions,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich, have occaſioned diſſatisfactions</l>
                  <l>In many of this <hi>Nation;</hi> or, as thou</l>
                  <l>Mayſt ſcandalize them, by thine <hi>actings</hi> now.</l>
                  <l>But, that, wherein thy <hi>reall proof</hi> will be,</l>
                  <l>Lockt, from <hi>mens eys,</hi> lyes hid, with <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>thee:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:116005:7"/>
                  <l>And, whatſoever thou reſolv'ſt upon,</l>
                  <l>Will either <hi>Well,</hi> or elſe <hi>not well,</hi> be done,</l>
                  <l>As, unto thoſe things, they relating are,</l>
                  <l>Which unto <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Thee alone,</hi> appear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The waſhing of th' <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> in the water</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Jordan,</hi> was but an indifferent matter,</l>
                  <l>Till made the <hi>ſole condition</hi> of his <hi>Cure:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, doubtleſſe, had not <hi>that,</hi> been in his pow'r,</l>
                  <l>He had been <hi>Cleanſ'd</hi> without it. <hi>David's ſin</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>Numb'ring of the People,</hi> lay not in</l>
                  <l>That <hi>ſimple Act;</hi> but, in the ſecret <hi>Pride</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Diſobedience,</hi> which did then reſide</l>
                  <l>Within his <hi>Heart;</hi> And, when it ſhall appear</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Thou,</hi> from <hi>Guiltineſs,</hi> art that way clear;</l>
                  <l>And, haſt repented all thoſe <hi>Humane failings,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which have, in ought, obſtructed thy <hi>Prevailings:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then, ſhall the <hi>gift-refuſed,</hi> neither be</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Scandall</hi> unto <hi>Others,</hi> or to <hi>Thee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Although accepted; when thou haſt reſiſted</l>
                  <l>So far, as <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> have aſſiſted.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, ſhould the <hi>Pow'r-Coordinate</hi> with thine,</l>
                  <l>O're-pow'r thee ſo, that, thou thereto incline</l>
                  <l>(Conſenting to their <hi>Motives</hi> at the laſt)</l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>Conſcience</hi> bearing witneſſe, that thou haſt</l>
                  <l>Complied there withall, rather by <hi>force</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Than <hi>Choiſe;</hi> to keep <hi>bad</hi> things, from being <hi>worſe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, if by ſtrength of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> ſwayd thou art</l>
                  <l>To that <hi>Acceptance;</hi> thou, haſt done thy part:</l>
                  <l>And, ſhalt by <hi>yeelding,</hi> paſs another Trial</l>
                  <l>As honourable, as, is this <hi>Denial.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt be ſafe, from all that was <hi>portended,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shouldſt thou by <hi>Levity,</hi> have condiſcended,</l>
                  <l>Or, tempted been by <hi>Self-neſs,</hi> to forgo</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Title,</hi> thou haſt owned hitherto;</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:116005:7"/>
                  <l>And wilt be free from blame, what ever ſhall</l>
                  <l>Hereafter, by the <hi>Change thereof</hi> befall.</l>
                  <l>For, nothing ſhall amiſſe to thee ſucceed,</l>
                  <l>By what, is not <hi>Thine,</hi> but, <hi>anothers deed.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No <hi>Reaſon,</hi> bindeth any to withſtand,</l>
                  <l>What, <hi>Pow'r,</hi> and <hi>ſtronger Reaſon,</hi> doth command;</l>
                  <l>And, when perhaps too, <hi>God,</hi> his ayde withdraws,</l>
                  <l>From thy aſſiſtance, in this <hi>dubious cauſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To bring on them, whats due for their <hi>offence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who truſt their own <hi>Wits,</hi> more than <hi>Providence.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This, I expreſſe here, not to leave a <hi>Gap</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whereby, thou may'ſt from <hi>Juſt Reſolves</hi> eſcape:</l>
                  <l>(For, God will find it out, if there be <hi>ought</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To ſuch a <hi>purpoſe,</hi> lurking in thy thought:)</l>
                  <l>But, that, thou may'ſt not fall into a <hi>Snare</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By things, which in themſelves, <hi>Indifferent are;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Nor <hi>good</hi> nor <hi>evill,</hi> but, as unto that</l>
                  <l>Which may be <hi>good,</hi> or <hi>Evill,</hi> they relate;)</l>
                  <l>And, to preſerve thine <hi>Honour,</hi> among thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who ſhall, perchance, their <hi>Expectations</hi> loſe</l>
                  <l>By what may come to paſſe; (yea, to prevent</l>
                  <l>That, which may thereof, be a <hi>Conſequent</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To thee diſſerviceable) I, am bold</l>
                  <l>To tell thee, what my <hi>Muſe</hi> to me hath told;</l>
                  <l>Which, dictates, otherwhile in <hi>Slighted rimes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, which doth much concern theſe <hi>preſent times;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, would, it may be, had it not been <hi>Mine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Suppos'd have been, an <hi>Off-ſpring, more divine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, I, my, <hi>Muſings</hi> now, to thoſe will bend</l>
                  <l>Who may, perhaps, miſtruſt what I intend.</l>
                  <l>Although I have, by this <hi>Anticipation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Preſented that unto conſideration,</l>
                  <l>Which may be profitable (if <hi>revers'd</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His <hi>purpoſe</hi> be, on Tearms before rehears'd)</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:116005:8"/>
                  <l>Yet, leaſt, I may with <hi>one hand,</hi> be ſuſpected</l>
                  <l>To <hi>pull down,</hi> what the <hi>other</hi> had <hi>Erected;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I will not ſmother ought, which I ſhall finde,</l>
                  <l>May juſtly fortifie him in the <hi>minde,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By him profeſt; untill, to drive him out</l>
                  <l>Of his <hi>Reſolve,</hi> Thoſe <hi>Reaſons</hi> may be brought,</l>
                  <l>Which will be <hi>ſtronger;</hi> leſt, ſome, ſhould ſurmize</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He;</hi> without <hi>Cauſe,</hi> deni'd what he denies;</l>
                  <l>Or, leſt my late <hi>Rejoycings,</hi> may appear</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Reaſonleſſe,</hi> as many think they were.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My <hi>gladneſſe</hi> of it, flow'd from no reſpect</l>
                  <l>Unto my <hi>ſelf,</hi> or, fears of an effect</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Kingſhip,</hi> which my <hi>profits</hi> might impair:</l>
                  <l>For, I have, that way, <hi>likelihoods</hi> more fair</l>
                  <l>Than I have now (if nothing it occaſions,</l>
                  <l>To break our <hi>Peace,</hi> at <hi>Home,</hi> or, by <hi>Invaſions</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From <hi>Foes abroad</hi>) nor can I ſcandal'd be,</l>
                  <l>Thereby, through ought, which will reflect on <hi>me:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, I <hi>rejoyced</hi> in it, for the ſake</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Him,</hi> who did this <hi>Title</hi> undertake;</l>
                  <l>And, for <hi>their ſakes,</hi> who <hi>Acted</hi> and <hi>Enacted,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Things, whereby poſſibly may be contracted</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Scandals;</hi> or, which may a new expoſe</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Country,</hi> to be ſpoiled by her <hi>Foes.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For <hi>theſe,</hi> and <hi>ſuch reſpects as theſe</hi> (together</l>
                  <l>With what may be again transferred hither,</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Heart,</hi> that was through <hi>fear</hi> of them, grown ſad,</l>
                  <l>Became through hope of their <hi>prevention,</hi> glad.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, what a <hi>black Scene,</hi> ſhould we here have ſeen?</l>
                  <l>How many <hi>greeved hearts,</hi> would here have been,</l>
                  <l>Had our <hi>Protector,</hi> either been eſtranged</l>
                  <l>From what he <hi>was,</hi> or, (<hi>ſeem'd to be</hi>) ſo changed,</l>
                  <l>As, lightly to forgo his intereſt</l>
                  <l>In that, wherewith he had been ſo much <hi>bleſt?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:116005:8"/>
                  <l>Or, ſhould by others, have been ſo deluded,</l>
                  <l>As, to let <hi>that</hi> upon him be obtruded,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>He himſelf</hi> diſclaim'd? and, may bring back</l>
                  <l>A <hi>King</hi> upon us, with his <hi>Pedlars Pack</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Vanities,</hi> which have been by this <hi>Nation</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Rejected by a <hi>ſolemn protestation:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, which are <hi>Trinckets,</hi> as unſeparable</l>
                  <l>From moſt <hi>Kings,</hi> as is from a Fool, his <hi>babble?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, there is nought more likely, in, to bring</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Him</hi> that's expelled, then, to make a <hi>King,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>At this time; and, to make on that accompt</l>
                  <l>(Which is <hi>deſign'd</hi>) that <hi>Title</hi> paramount:</l>
                  <l>Nor can there be, for what our <hi>Foe</hi> intends,</l>
                  <l>A better <hi>ground-worke</hi> laid, by all his <hi>friends.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theſe things I feared;</hi> and, my <hi>ſoul</hi> foreſees</l>
                  <l>That, all thoſe things may creep in by degrees,</l>
                  <l>Which, to the <hi>Kingdomes</hi> of this World pertain;</l>
                  <l>Which, may inſlave the <hi>Saints</hi> of <hi>God</hi> again;</l>
                  <l>And, which, may in a ſhort time, reinveſt</l>
                  <l>With that <hi>pow'r,</hi> which impowred <hi>Antichriſt:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Unleſſe, it by his <hi>Mercy,</hi> be withſtood</l>
                  <l>Whoſe <hi>wiſdome,</hi> can from <hi>Evil,</hi> bring forth <hi>Good.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theſe things I fear'd,</hi> and if a <hi>Parlament</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Can make a <hi>King,</hi> which may theſe <hi>fears</hi> prevent;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Him,</hi> and his <hi>Nobles,</hi> if it can ſo bind,</l>
                  <l>That, we may be ſecured in this kind;</l>
                  <l>And keep our <hi>Sov'raign,</hi> and theſe <hi>Nations</hi> free</l>
                  <l>From <hi>ſcandals,</hi> which occaſioned may be;</l>
                  <l>I, ſhould not only yeild, on that condition</l>
                  <l>To make a <hi>King,</hi> but beg one by <hi>Petition.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Redouble, that <hi>rejoycing,</hi> which appear'd,</l>
                  <l>When, of what was <hi>reſolved,</hi> I firſt heard:</l>
                  <l>And, make my <hi>heart,</hi> the <hi>firſt ſtep</hi> whereupon</l>
                  <l>He might ſet foot, to mount up to his <hi>Throne:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:116005:9"/>
                  <l>Yea, ſing a <hi>Panegyrick</hi> in their praiſe</l>
                  <l>Who mov'd it, that ſhould long out-laſt my daies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We look for ſuch a <hi>Government,</hi> as ſhall</l>
                  <l>Make way for <hi>Chriſt:</hi> not that fantaſtical</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fifth Monarchie,</hi> whereof ſome people dream,</l>
                  <l>And Conquer would an <hi>Earthly Throne</hi> for him</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Carnal weapons:</hi> But, that, <hi>preſent</hi> here</l>
                  <l>He, may ſo be, and ſo to <hi>reign,</hi> appear</l>
                  <l>As he hath <hi>promis'd;</hi> and, that <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Truth,</hi> may ev'ry <hi>Throne</hi> on Earth poſſeſs,</l>
                  <l>According to that meaſure of his <hi>grace,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which is apportion'd, to this <hi>earthly place.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His <hi>Highneſs,</hi> hath made progreſs in a <hi>path</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As far forth toward it, as any hath</l>
                  <l>Since <hi>Chriſt</hi> aſcended; if, the <hi>Depths</hi> and <hi>Heights,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Rugged paſſages,</hi> and <hi>Narrow Streights</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Conſider'd be, through which his <hi>March</hi> he makes,</l>
                  <l>To bring to end the <hi>Work</hi> he undertakes.</l>
                  <l>He muſt now paſs a <hi>Rock,</hi> which will require</l>
                  <l>An <hi>Ingeneer</hi> with <hi>Vineger</hi> and <hi>fire;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, cut a <hi>Paſſage,</hi> which (as by a <hi>thread</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Muſt on each <hi>hand,</hi> ev'n to a <hi>hairs-breadth,</hi> lead</l>
                  <l>'Twixt <hi>Conſcience</hi> and ſound <hi>Reaſon:</hi> whence, to vary</l>
                  <l>Were irrecoverably to miſcarry.</l>
                  <l>Oh <hi>God!</hi> aſſiſt him; and, to what I pray</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Amen,</hi> let all, who wiſh our welfare, ſay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He, hitherto, in that which he hath done,</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Work,</hi> with prudency, hath carried on:</l>
                  <l>And, firm to his own <hi>Principles</hi> abides,</l>
                  <l>Though many ſtrive to bring him to their <hi>ſides:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yea, though there be ſome too, of whom he may</l>
                  <l>(As <hi>David</hi> of <hi>Zerviah</hi>'s Sons did ſay)</l>
                  <l>Complain, that, they, were oft for him, too hard;</l>
                  <l>Yet, <hi>Him</hi> from his <hi>Reſolves</hi> they have not ſtirr'd.</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:116005:9"/>
                  <l>And (be it well conſidered of all you,</l>
                  <l>Who <hi>read this,</hi> and, perchance miſcenſure now</l>
                  <l>Of his <hi>Heroick Act</hi>) he doth not wave</l>
                  <l>Ought neceſſary for a <hi>Prince</hi> to have;</l>
                  <l>Which had been a <hi>Denial,</hi> in effect,</l>
                  <l>Of that <hi>Pow'r,</hi> which his <hi>People</hi> ſhould protect;</l>
                  <l>And, were no <hi>Self-denial,</hi> (as I gather)</l>
                  <l>But, a denial of his <hi>Duty</hi> rather.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Kingſhip</hi> is not wav'd, but, as it tends</l>
                  <l>To what may much diſconſolate his <hi>friends,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or glad his <hi>foes;</hi> And, which, as things yet ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Relating to <hi>Pre-actings</hi> in this Land,</l>
                  <l>Might draw on very evil <hi>Conſequences;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or give juſt cauſe of many great <hi>Offences:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Could theſe removed, or prevented be,</l>
                  <l>So that his <hi>Conſcience,</hi> might from them be free,</l>
                  <l>Perchance, <hi>That,</hi> to take place it would permit</l>
                  <l>As <hi>rational,</hi> which ſo appears not yet.</l>
                  <l>For to the <hi>Clean,</hi> he knows all things are <hi>Clean,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And (if I gueſs aright what he doth mean)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That,</hi> whereof, he doth chiefly <hi>ſcruple</hi> make,</l>
                  <l>Is, <hi>Giving an offence unto the weak;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, <hi>that,</hi> therewith, all things now ſtartled at</l>
                  <l>Might paſs, when he upon them ſhall debate,</l>
                  <l>If <hi>God,</hi> informs his <hi>Conſcience,</hi> that they may;</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Reaſon</hi> ſhall his <hi>Reaſons</hi> overſway.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He nothing hath refus'd with diſreſpect</l>
                  <l>To <hi>them who offer'd it:</hi> Or, with neglect</l>
                  <l>Of ought propos'd for <hi>Publick benefit:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, only, what may poſſibly beget</l>
                  <l>More <hi>Jealouſie</hi> than <hi>Love:</hi> more <hi>Envy,</hi> then</l>
                  <l>Glory to <hi>God,</hi> or good to <hi>Honeſt men.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, he by his <hi>Refuſal,</hi> unto none</l>
                  <l>Denyeth ought, but, to himſelf alone;</l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:116005:10"/>
                  <l>Or, that, which he doth probably believe</l>
                  <l>Will marre our <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>Civil wars</hi> revive:</l>
                  <l>For which, if <hi>worſe,</hi> he rather ſpeed than <hi>better,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His <hi>merit</hi> is the more; his <hi>praiſe</hi> the greater;</l>
                  <l>And, they, who ſhall the leſſe <hi>affection</hi> ſhow him,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>that,</hi> deny the <hi>duty</hi> which they owe him.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What, if he thinks the changing of his <hi>Title,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Implies a <hi>levitie,</hi> which doth but little</l>
                  <l>Beſeeme a <hi>Prince?</hi> and may occaſion too</l>
                  <l>A <hi>quarrell,</hi> which might all his work undo?</l>
                  <l>Or propagate a miſchievous effect,</l>
                  <l>To their deſtruction whom he ſhould protect?</l>
                  <l>Is he not bound in <hi>Conſcience</hi> to beware</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch a <hi>Title,</hi> whoſoe're they are</l>
                  <l>That ſhall propoſe it? ſhould he not betray</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Truſt,</hi> by giving eaſily away</l>
                  <l>That <hi>earneſt</hi> of <hi>Protection,</hi> which doth ſeem</l>
                  <l>To be, by <hi>God,</hi> conferred upon him</l>
                  <l>For ſafeguard of his <hi>Saints?</hi> or, might there not</l>
                  <l>Some blemiſh be in <hi>Reputation</hi> got,</l>
                  <l>Relating to that <hi>Stile?</hi> if, he, the ſame</l>
                  <l>Should change for <hi>that,</hi> by which their <hi>bondage</hi> came?</l>
                  <l>And can he think it nothing <hi>ſignifies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, <hi>they,</hi> who are his greateſt <hi>Enemies</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Do more rejoyce, in that which was intended,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>they,</hi> by whom, he hath been beſt befriended?</l>
                  <l>If, likewiſe, with a ſerious heed, he ſhall</l>
                  <l>Be pleaſed to conſider therewithall,</l>
                  <l>What kind of <hi>men,</hi> the <hi>greateſt number</hi> are</l>
                  <l>Who, for this <hi>change</hi> moſt zealous do appear;</l>
                  <l>What <hi>Intereſt</hi> it is, which they would ſave:</l>
                  <l>What <hi>Principles,</hi> the moſt among them have;</l>
                  <l>Can he ſuppoſe, more ſafe for him, it were</l>
                  <l>To <hi>theſe,</hi> then to his <hi>beſt friends,</hi> to adhere?</l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:116005:10"/>
                  <l>Whoſe <hi>Converſations,</hi> are to him well known?</l>
                  <l>Whoſe <hi>cauſe</hi> is his? Whoſe <hi>principles</hi> his owne?</l>
                  <l>Since, <hi>Reaſon</hi> doth incline him, to the <hi>laſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Conſcience,</hi> too, the ballance that way caſt?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That <hi>Title,</hi> which hath hitherto been own'd,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>victories</hi> and <hi>bleſſings,</hi> hath been crown'd;</l>
                  <l>It, now, hath rendered it <hi>ſelfe</hi> exempt</l>
                  <l>For ever, from that undeſerv'd <hi>contempt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which <hi>novelty</hi> occaſion'd; and, throughout</l>
                  <l>The <hi>World,</hi> is with much <hi>honour</hi> ſpread about.</l>
                  <l>He, thereby had a <hi>pow'r,</hi> which lately ſhook</l>
                  <l>The wals of <hi>Babel;</hi> and with terror ſtrooke</l>
                  <l>His <hi>proudeſt foes;</hi> and, is it vaniſh'd, now,</l>
                  <l>We neither know <hi>when</hi> or by <hi>what,</hi> or <hi>how?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Except it be, for thankleſly deſpiſing</l>
                  <l>So <hi>prosperous a Stile,</hi> and idolizing</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>that,</hi> which forced us, in our <hi>affliction</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To take up that we have, for our <hi>protection.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When, <hi>Iſrael</hi> would be <hi>King-rid,</hi> God, to ſhew</l>
                  <l>His anger, and, what thereon would enſue,</l>
                  <l>Deſtroy'd in <hi>Harveſt time,</hi> their corne with ſhowers;</l>
                  <l>And at the <hi>Seed-time,</hi> he did hazzard ours</l>
                  <l>By extream <hi>Drought;</hi> untill that was deny'd</l>
                  <l>Which is propos'd; and, then, forthwith ſuppli'de</l>
                  <l>Our preſent <hi>want:</hi> perhaps, to make us ſeek</l>
                  <l>His <hi>will,</hi> and, know our <hi>ſinne,</hi> and theirs alike:</l>
                  <l>Leſt, in his <hi>wrath,</hi> he give us what we crave,</l>
                  <l>And take away, what he in <hi>mercy</hi> gave.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What will enſue, by ſetling <hi>Kingſhip</hi> here,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>common good,</hi> it doth not yet appeare:</l>
                  <l>Some, doe pretend, it render will, to us,</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>laws</hi> more fixt, and much more vigorous,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe, by <hi>Kings,</hi> they were to us deriv'd,</l>
                  <l>And confirmation in their name receiv'd.</l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:116005:11"/>
                  <l>But, wherefore, may not all that, which relates</l>
                  <l>To <hi>King,</hi> or <hi>People, Freedoms,</hi> or <hi>Eſtates</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In our <hi>preceding Laws,</hi> be ſo Compacted</l>
                  <l>Into one <hi>Statute,</hi> now to be <hi>Enacted,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, they may by his <hi>Highneſſes</hi> aſſent,</l>
                  <l>Be made as firm, as this new <hi>Inſtrument,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By our <hi>Protector,</hi> who, muſt be the <hi>Stone</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Firſt laid, to build their <hi>new fram'd work upon?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why may not <hi>He,</hi> who now is our <hi>Supream,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Make both unto <hi>Himſelf,</hi> and unto <hi>them</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who ask it of him, all our <hi>Laws</hi> forepaſt</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Uſeful,</hi> and as <hi>Binding,</hi> as this <hi>Laſt?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Why may not <hi>He,</hi> who is a <hi>Conquerer</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For Us, and did for us, receive his <hi>Pow'r</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Confirm our <hi>Laws,</hi> or any other thing,</l>
                  <l>(As ſtrongly, as if he were call'd a <hi>King</hi>)</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Us,</hi> and to <hi>Himſelf,</hi> with their conſent,</l>
                  <l>Who by his <hi>Pow'r,</hi> are made a <hi>Parlament?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Why, ſhould it unto him, ought leſs afford,</l>
                  <l>Than to all <hi>Princes,</hi> raiſed by the <hi>Sword?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No man, can juſtly, that to him denay.</l>
                  <l>For, <hi>Conqueſt</hi> is the ordinary way,</l>
                  <l>Whereby, God changeth <hi>Governments,</hi> and flings</l>
                  <l>From off their <hi>Thrones,</hi> great <hi>Emperors</hi> and <hi>Kings.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And 'tis <hi>Gods mercy,</hi> not our own deſert,</l>
                  <l>Which, hitherto, hath ſo inclin'd his heart,</l>
                  <l>That, though he hath been ſtraightned more than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Arbitrary actings</hi> were not many;</l>
                  <l>Nor, till they were conſtrain'd by ſome diſtreſs,</l>
                  <l>For preſervation of the <hi>Publick Peace.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Some, think it will <hi>Secure</hi> his <hi>Perſon</hi> more,</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>Charge</hi> the <hi>People</hi> leſs, than heretofore,</l>
                  <l>To ſtile him <hi>King.</hi> But, theſe men much miſtake,</l>
                  <l>And, will perceive they <hi>Dream,</hi> when they awake:</l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:116005:11"/>
                  <l>For, can we think, when he away hath thrown</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Title,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> gave to be his own,</l>
                  <l>Without a <hi>Rival,</hi> that, aſſume he may</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Name,</hi> whereto another claim doth lay,</l>
                  <l>With greater <hi>Safety?</hi> Is there ſome new <hi>charm,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Infus'd into that <hi>word,</hi> to guard from harm?</l>
                  <l>Or, will it make the <hi>Royaliſts</hi> more true</l>
                  <l>To him, becauſe, he takes what they think due,</l>
                  <l>Unto another? Quite deſert the <hi>Lord,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They own'd, and, do their homage to a <hi>word?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, (where they hated) <hi>Loyaltie</hi> profeſs</l>
                  <l>Rather, for doing <hi>More wrong,</hi> than for leſs?</l>
                  <l>So fooliſh can we think them, as, to prize</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Complement,</hi> which nothing ſignifies,</l>
                  <l>Save, either ſome poor <hi>Hope,</hi> or vain <hi>Deſire</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To be in <hi>Us,</hi> which may advance them higher,</l>
                  <l>In thoſe <hi>Reſolves,</hi> which they had heretofore?</l>
                  <l>And, make our <hi>Dangers</hi> no whit <hi>Leſs,</hi> but <hi>more?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, when they do perceive our <hi>Giddineſs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our <hi>falling from,</hi> thoſe things we did profeſs,</l>
                  <l>Our doating on thoſe <hi>Bawbles,</hi> which we ſeem'd</l>
                  <l>Not much (a while ago) to have eſteem'd,</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Taking up,</hi> what we had <hi>Thrown away,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our ſleighting that, to <hi>Morrow,</hi> which this day</l>
                  <l>We made a Law; and that our <hi>Proteſtations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Were for the moſt part, but <hi>Diſſimulations;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thence, they will take occaſion to conclude</l>
                  <l>That, we have, <hi>all along,</hi> ſuch <hi>Ends</hi> purſude</l>
                  <l>As they have had: And, that, what ere to ſeem</l>
                  <l>We have made <hi>Shew,</hi> we are juſt like to <hi>Them.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, we did <hi>wade</hi> and <hi>ſwim,</hi> through <hi>ſtreams</hi> of blood,</l>
                  <l>Not to accompliſh what is <hi>Just</hi> and <hi>Good;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, to obtain our <hi>Luſts:</hi> That, we have ſought</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Policy,</hi> and by our <hi>Battails</hi> fought,</l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:116005:12"/>
                  <l>Againſt <hi>Oppoſers;</hi> not ſo much to ſave</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Liberties,</hi> as, others to <hi>inſlave:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, our <hi>contests,</hi> were not for <hi>God,</hi> or, for</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Country;</hi> but, (which <hi>Goodmen</hi> will abhor</l>
                  <l>To think upon) our <hi>owne ſelves,</hi> to inveſt</l>
                  <l>With, that, which was by other men poſſeſt:</l>
                  <l>That, being <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> in all we did,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Cloaks of ſanctity,</hi> the ſame we hid,</l>
                  <l>Thereby, to draw in thoſe who were ſincere,</l>
                  <l>To be deceiv'd, in what we made appear.</l>
                  <l>(Ev'n to the ruine, of their <hi>Children, Wives,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Peace,</hi> their <hi>Freedoms,</hi> their <hi>Estates,</hi> their <hi>Lives</hi>)</l>
                  <l>That, we might get <hi>high Titles,</hi> large <hi>Poſſeſſions,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Prerogatives,</hi> by their <hi>oppreſſions,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, that inſtead of ſetting <hi>Chriſt</hi> upon</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Throne,</hi> we, might inſtall our <hi>ſelves</hi> thereon.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This will be thought:</hi> And, <hi>they</hi> who are our <hi>Foes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Will peradventure, thereupon ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>That <hi>God</hi> is not <hi>among us,</hi> as they fear'd;</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>for us,</hi> as it formerly appear'd;</l>
                  <l>And, thence take courage, to begin again</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That,</hi> which they hitherto purſu'd in vain.</l>
                  <l>And, ſuch will be the <hi>ſafety,</hi> which your <hi>King</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Unto <hi>Himſelf,</hi> and <hi>us,</hi> is like to bring.</l>
                  <l>Good God! how are they chang'd? how ſtupifi'd?</l>
                  <l>By whom theſe dangers are not yet eſpi'd?</l>
                  <l>How blind, doth <hi>ſelfneſs,</hi> make us quickly grow,</l>
                  <l>In that, which might prevent <hi>ſelfe-overthrow?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Will <hi>Kingſhip,</hi> make him ſafer than he was?</l>
                  <l>How may that be? how can it come to paſs?</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Title,</hi> not much more then eight years paſt,</l>
                  <l>Could not preſerve his <hi>Head,</hi> who reigned laſt.</l>
                  <l>No, not preſerve him, from the <hi>dreadfull fate,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of dying on a <hi>Scaffold,</hi> at his gate:</l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:116005:12"/>
                  <l>And, if all things be weighed well together</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Stile,</hi> as poſſibly may <hi>bring</hi> him thither,</l>
                  <l>Who ruleth now; yea, and a <hi>tragical</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Effect therewith, perhaps, upon us all,</l>
                  <l>Before the malice of our <hi>foes</hi> is ended,</l>
                  <l>How ſafe ſoe're, to be, it is pretended.</l>
                  <l>We may perceive, (unleſſe we will deſpiſe,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Light within us,</hi> and feel up our eyes,)</l>
                  <l>There is no <hi>likelyheod,</hi> it will abate</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>fury,</hi> who purſue us with their <hi>hate;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, ſo increaſe it, that it will <hi>increaſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>dangers,</hi> which we dream, it will make <hi>leſſe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yea, make <hi>Him,</hi> whoſe <hi>ſafe being</hi> it pretends,</l>
                  <l>Vnſafe among thoſe, who have been his <hi>Friends,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, <hi>them</hi> among <hi>themſelves:</hi> It will go near,</l>
                  <l>To make men of <hi>themſelves,</hi> to ſtand in fear.</l>
                  <l>It will increaſe <hi>ſuſpitions,</hi> till th'effect</l>
                  <l>Grows worſe, than many of us can ſuſpect:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Divide,</hi> and <hi>ſubdivide,</hi> till there be nought</l>
                  <l>Left poſſible to be <hi>ſaid, done,</hi> or <hi>thought;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To cure the <hi>miſchieves,</hi> which will be effected;</l>
                  <l>(And are by ſome, both <hi>hop'd for,</hi> and <hi>projected;</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Except in <hi>mercy, He,</hi> that heretofore</l>
                  <l>Hath oft ſo done; ſhall (pleaſed be) once more,</l>
                  <l>To draw forth an <hi>Expedient,</hi> from our <hi>failing,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, will for our advantage, be <hi>prevailing.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>More might be ſaid; but, ought more to expreſſe</l>
                  <l>Would be in vain to thoſe, who cannot gueſſe</l>
                  <l>The reſt by this. And, yet, becauſe the <hi>reaſon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>ſaving charges,</hi> comes in ſuch a <hi>ſeaſon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As gives it <hi>weight;</hi> Let us examine, whether</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Seaſon,</hi> and the <hi>thrift,</hi> agree together,</l>
                  <l>Leſt, in that <hi>frugal humour</hi> we may die,</l>
                  <l>And, gain an <hi>Epitaph,</hi> like this, thereby:</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:116005:13"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Here, lies interr'd the Miſer, Father</hi> Sparges,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who might have liv'd: but died to ſave charges.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I find your <hi>Thrift,</hi> you, think we might <hi>disband</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>Armies,</hi> which are quarter'd through this Land,</l>
                  <l>If our <hi>Protector</hi> were proclaim'd a <hi>King.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It may be ſo; and I, the ſelf ſame thing</l>
                  <l>Should alſo think; if I conſidered not,</l>
                  <l>We might thereby, as good as <hi>Cut our throat.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is any man ſo voyd of <hi>Common ſenſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As, not to ſee what might reſult from thence?</l>
                  <l>May we not ſave the charge of paying <hi>One,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, let <hi>Two Armies</hi> in, when that is gone,</l>
                  <l>To pay <hi>themſelves,</hi> until at laſt, they ſhall</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Contributions,</hi> and in <hi>Pay</hi> have all?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You fear, perhaps, that by the <hi>Souldierie</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Laws,</hi> our <hi>Freedoms,</hi> and <hi>Proprietie</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May be deſtroy'd, if long imbodied here;</l>
                  <l>And, cauſe enough there may be of that fear:</l>
                  <l>But, will a <hi>King,</hi> prevent it? may not we</l>
                  <l>Another way as much oppreſſed be,</l>
                  <l>By ſome, who for our <hi>Liberties</hi> pretend</l>
                  <l>Yet, Cry up <hi>Kingſhip,</hi> for their <hi>private end?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May we not ſuffer at the <hi>Lawyers Bar,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As much as we endured by the <hi>War,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Through thoſe <hi>Formalities,</hi> which make the <hi>Laws,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of our moſt <hi>ſad oppreſſion,</hi> one chief cauſe?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>Sword</hi> unſufferably, (I confeſs)</l>
                  <l>If not well <hi>diſciplin'd,</hi> will us oppreſs:</l>
                  <l>But, hitherto, it hath been in thoſe <hi>hands,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which kept it ſerviceable in theſe <hi>Lands,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With ſo much <hi>Moderation,</hi> that no time,</l>
                  <l>Bears witneſs of the like in any <hi>Clime:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, though an Inſolent <hi>proud Fool</hi> or twain,</l>
                  <l>Cauſe, to ſome few, hath given to complain,</l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:116005:13"/>
                  <l>Their <hi>Arbitrary actings,</hi> were not many;</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>or to the ruine, or great loſs of any.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>onder, any man can ſtand inawe</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Swords</hi> and <hi>Guns,</hi> who feels the plague of <hi>Lawe;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>d, would not rather be devoured <hi>twice</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Lions,</hi> than once eaten up with <hi>Lice.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ould I illuſtrate (which, my private wrong</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>y, peradventure, force me to e're long)</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e <hi>ſad diſcoveries</hi> which I have made</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ce firſt that <hi>Gangreeve,</hi> I, upon me had;</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> what impertinent <hi>vexatious wayes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ſtly devices, or undue <hi>delayes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e Suits of wronged <hi>Clients</hi> forth are ſpun,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>re than twice <hi>twenty years,</hi> and yet not done;</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> what exceſſive <hi>Fees</hi> (twice or thrice tooke)</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ithout one <hi>Line writ down,</hi> or one <hi>word spoke,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>d, at how dear a rate they ſometimes buy</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ain hope,</hi> which augments their miſery;</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>w, <hi>Motions, Orders,</hi> and <hi>Reports</hi> beget</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>h other, till their <hi>brood</hi> grows <hi>Infinit;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>d, how ſome <hi>Regiſters,</hi> put <hi>out,</hi> or <hi>in,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>oſe <hi>words,</hi> which may another <hi>Round</hi> begin,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>hough they who heard the <hi>Judges</hi> Order, thought</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e <hi>Cauſe,</hi> would thereby to an end be brought)</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>u would ſuppoſe (and might ſuppoſe it well)</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e <hi>Courts</hi> we toyl in, were ſome <hi>Rooms in Hell,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>d, that, we had impoſed there on us</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e never ending Plague of <hi>Syſiphus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>o, up a <hi>Steep hill,</hi> rowled with great pain</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Weighty Stone,</hi> which ſtill <hi>rowl'd down again.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Should I declare, how frequently our <hi>Lawes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e pleaded to maintain a <hi>wicked cauſe;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>w rarely, <hi>good ſucceſs</hi> on him attends,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>o makes not way, by <hi>Kindred, Bribes,</hi> or <hi>Friends:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:116005:14"/>
                  <l>What <hi>hazzards</hi> he is in, to be betrai'd,</l>
                  <l>By them, for whoſe aſſiſtance, he hath paid?</l>
                  <l>And, then, how <hi>far about,</hi> they make him run</l>
                  <l>E're they will ſuffer him to be <hi>undone,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>You, would not greatly fear (no not at all)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Courts-martial,</hi> or a <hi>Major Generall,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, rather, fear to fall into their <hi>claws,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who, to mens ruine, turne our <hi>wholſome Laws,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe <hi>practiſe,</hi> being <hi>regulated,</hi> might</l>
                  <l>Preſerve our <hi>private</hi> and our <hi>publick Right:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, that, our <hi>Laws</hi> are good, confeſſe I do,</l>
                  <l>And, that, we have ſome <hi>honeſt Lawyers,</hi> too.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No men have more oppreſſed been of late</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This way,</hi> then, they who beſt have ſerv'd this <hi>State,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And to ſupport it, did themſelves expoſe</l>
                  <l>To <hi>hazzards,</hi> by accepting what our <hi>Foes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had <hi>forfeited,</hi> to be therewith repay'd,</l>
                  <l>When, others, of ſuch <hi>bargains</hi> were afraid:</l>
                  <l>For, if it were obſerv'd, how they have ſleighted</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>Acts of Parlament,</hi> which, us invited</l>
                  <l>Vpon the <hi>Publick credit,</hi> to lay forth</l>
                  <l>Our ſelves, for <hi>Titles</hi> of ſuch little worth</l>
                  <l>In moſt mens value, that, but few or none</l>
                  <l>Will take thereof, <hi>ten pounds,</hi> in <hi>pledg</hi> for <hi>one;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It would appear, that, wee, among the reſt</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe by them griev'd, have been moſt oppreſt.</l>
                  <l>For my own part, I, now <hi>five years</hi> together,</l>
                  <l>Have ſought for <hi>Justice,</hi> and can yet get neither</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Land</hi> nor <hi>Money:</hi> though by further coſt,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>thouſand pounds</hi> are added to what's loſt;</l>
                  <l>Nor whither, for <hi>redreſs</hi> I may retire,</l>
                  <l>Do I yet know; nor where, I can <hi>enquire:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, ſhould I in each <hi>circumstance,</hi> declare</l>
                  <l>My wrongs thereby, and what <hi>effects</hi> they are</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:116005:14"/>
                  <l>Which thence have followed you would ſay, the <hi>ſword</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>erewith compared, <hi>Mercies</hi> did afford;</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>d, that, it more to our vexation tends,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> be deſtroyed by our <hi>ſeeming-friends,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ith lingring torments; then, with one great <hi>blow,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>be made <hi>ſenſleſs,</hi> by an <hi>open Foe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>d, therefore, when I have conſidered well</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>hat I (and many moe) in this kind feel,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>re conclude, that if no courſe be found,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>hereby, that <hi>Justice,</hi> may be here inthron'd,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>hich will redreſs theſe <hi>wrongs</hi> (and thoſe that lye</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>houſands of <hi>Petitions</hi> hurled by,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ithout regard) the <hi>ſword,</hi> will act <hi>once more;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>d, prove (I fear) more <hi>ſharpe</hi> than heretofore,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>annag'd by a <hi>King;</hi> which, both to <hi>us,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>d to <hi>himſelf,</hi> will now be <hi>ominous.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When we have made a <hi>King,</hi> which, will inlarge</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e <hi>common burthen,</hi> by a further charge,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>d added to the <hi>multitudes</hi> of thoſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ich now are <hi>known, new bands,</hi> of <hi>boſome foes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>o, mad with <hi>vengeance,</hi> and with diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ll any way, their brutiſh <hi>paſſions</hi> vent;</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ll it be <hi>thriftineſs,</hi> the charge to ſpare</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>t, ſhould for ſuch a time, a <hi>guard</hi> prepare?</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>eed, they few <hi>good pennyworths</hi> afford,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>o meaſure all things, by the <hi>Pike</hi> and <hi>Sword;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>d none of us, I think, could well abide</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Suits</hi> ſhould in a <hi>Martial Court</hi> be tri'd;</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>r, where they mannag'd are, till we could get</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>re <hi>expedition,</hi> than we can have yet,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>h leſs <hi>expence</hi>) but, better ſure it were,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſpend a little quantity of <hi>tarre</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>en loſe a <hi>Hog;</hi> and, to be ſome while willing</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſaving of a <hi>Pound,</hi> to pay a <hi>Shilling.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:116005:15"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hard things,</hi> in great <hi>ſtraights,</hi> muſt be undergone</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Offenſive guards,</hi> are better much than <hi>none.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Are you aſleep?</hi> and, ſee you not already</l>
                  <l>That, being in our <hi>Purpoſes</hi> unſteady,</l>
                  <l>Makes <hi>Bees,</hi> as well as <hi>Waſps,</hi> to <hi>Buz</hi> and <hi>Humme,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſhew their <hi>Stings,</hi> portending what will come</l>
                  <l>Do not you hear what's <hi>murmur'd,</hi> as among</l>
                  <l>The <hi>People,</hi> to and fro, you paſs along?</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>know you not,</hi> that, what is voyc'd abroad</l>
                  <l>By <hi>them,</hi> is otherwhile, the <hi>Voyce of God?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then, <hi>know it now;</hi> leſt, ſhortly, that be ſpoke</l>
                  <l>Which, when once ſaid, <hi>he never will revoke:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, though you ſleight the <hi>Scriblings of my Pen,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Learn wiſdome, from your prudent <hi>Huſband-men.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Doth any ſober <hi>Countrey Fellow,</hi> judge</l>
                  <l>He ſaveth ought, by pulling up his <hi>hedge</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Before his <hi>Corn</hi> be hous'd, to leave (the while</l>
                  <l>He therewith warms himſelf) his <hi>Crop</hi> to ſpoile?</l>
                  <l>Or, put away his <hi>Dogs,</hi> that were imploy'd</l>
                  <l>To guard the <hi>Sheep,</hi> till <hi>Wolves</hi> are quite deſtroy'd?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Conſider theſe things;</hi> And, by theſe conceive</l>
                  <l>What <hi>Prudence</hi> doth obliege us to believe</l>
                  <l>Of all thoſe other <hi>Arguments,</hi> you bring</l>
                  <l>To make us change <hi>Protector</hi> into <hi>King;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, to diſarm theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> till we ſee</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Common-wealth</hi> ſhall better ſetled bee.</l>
                  <l>But, 'tis the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of a <hi>Parlament,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which to our <hi>Prince,</hi> a <hi>Kingſhip</hi> doth preſent.</l>
                  <l>True; And, it is the <hi>Reaſon of the Prince,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Yea, and his <hi>Conſcience,</hi> too) which takes <hi>offence</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>At what is <hi>offer'd;</hi> and 'tis not a <hi>caſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As yet decided, whether ſhould give place.</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Private Reaſons,</hi> they might overſway,</l>
                  <l>And, though 'twere not <hi>convinc'd,</hi> I muſt obey,</l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:116005:15"/>
                  <l>Or <hi>Suffer:</hi> And thus for my <hi>Conſcience</hi> too</l>
                  <l>It muſt be, in things, which I cannot <hi>doe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But ſure, his <hi>Highneſs</hi> (if it may be judg'd</l>
                  <l>By <hi>private men</hi>) is much more <hi>Privileg'd:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, he whom <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>Raiſed up,</hi> or <hi>Sent</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To lay the <hi>Ground-work</hi> of a <hi>Government,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is with a <hi>Spirit,</hi> in all likelyhood</l>
                  <l>By him who rais'd him, for that <hi>work</hi> indow'd;</l>
                  <l>Yea peradventure, he is qualifide</l>
                  <l>To that <hi>End,</hi> more than <hi>all men elſe beſide,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As will appear (though this to ſome ſeem ſtrange)</l>
                  <l>If we look back on every former <hi>change;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And when to new <hi>Works, GOD</hi> doth <hi>Princes</hi> call,</l>
                  <l>What <hi>Spirits,</hi> them he furniſhes withall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Both <hi>Parlaments,</hi> and <hi>Councels general,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Do many times into great errors fall;</l>
                  <l>And for their <hi>Owne,</hi> or for the <hi>Peoples Sin</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Or for ſome <hi>other cauſes</hi>) oft have been</l>
                  <l>Deſerted by their <hi>Guide;</hi> that, men may know</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Weal,</hi> from their <hi>Joint wiſdome,</hi> doth not flow.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>God</hi> will prove a <hi>People,</hi> or a <hi>Prince,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It muſt, by ſomewhat, likely to <hi>convince,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Attempted be: The <hi>Spirit,</hi> to be tride,</l>
                  <l>In ſomewhat, muſt <hi>imbodied</hi> abide</l>
                  <l>That's <hi>venerable:</hi> elſe, no <hi>Approbation</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Can thereon follow, worth Conſideration.</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Prophet,</hi> by a <hi>Prophet</hi> was deceiv'd;</l>
                  <l>And yet, was therefore of his <hi>life</hi> bereav'd.</l>
                  <l>It was ev'n by thoſe men who ſeated were</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Moſes chair,</hi> (and whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> bad them hear)</l>
                  <l>Who did ſo miſadviſe them, that, they cri'd</l>
                  <l>To have the <hi>King of glory</hi> crucifi'd.</l>
                  <l>Yet, they have been <hi>accurſed</hi> till this day,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe, they did not as well <hi>try,</hi> and <hi>weigh,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:116005:16"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As hear</hi> their <hi>counſell;</hi> having, ſo to do,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>rule of Faith,</hi> and <hi>Light within</hi> them, too.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Reaſon,</hi> therefore, of a <hi>Parlament,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May be demurr'd upon, though it preſent</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A Kingdome:</hi> and, if any man may be</l>
                  <l>Thus <hi>privileg'd,</hi> then, no man more than he</l>
                  <l>Whom, it now moſt concerneth; and, who, muſt</l>
                  <l>Give an accompt, for what he hath in <hi>truſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, there is ſomething, that perſwades my heart,</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Parlament,</hi> in acting of their part</l>
                  <l>Hath not alone, done that which <hi>providence</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Will make to be, at laſt, without offence;</l>
                  <l>But, ſerviceable alſo to that end.</l>
                  <l>Which, <hi>God,</hi> and our <hi>Protector,</hi> did intend:</l>
                  <l>Or, that they will, at leaſt wiſe, have a care</l>
                  <l>That nothing ſhall be urged to inſnare</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Conſcience;</hi> or, be further on him preſt</l>
                  <l>Then ſo far, as the <hi>publick intereſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>his,</hi> it may advance: For, theſe are <hi>gifts</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That often have put many to <hi>hard ſhifts</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To get them; but, till now I ne'r did know</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A Prince,</hi> that might not ſuch a <hi>gift</hi> forego</l>
                  <l>VVithout <hi>offence;</hi> or, that a <hi>Conquerour,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To chuſe his <hi>Title</hi> had not alwayes power.</l>
                  <l>Nor can I think, that, he did ſo diſpoſe</l>
                  <l>Of his <hi>whole pow'r,</hi> when he impowred thoſe</l>
                  <l>For his <hi>aſſiſtance,</hi> that, <hi>himſelf</hi> he left</l>
                  <l>But as a <hi>Cypher,</hi> of all <hi>pow'r</hi> bereft:</l>
                  <l>Ev'n of <hi>enablement,</hi> by his <hi>negation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For that, which tendeth to the preſervation</l>
                  <l>Of his own <hi>conſcience:</hi> and, of meanes to do</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That,</hi> which the <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> binds him to:</l>
                  <l>For, their <hi>Petition,</hi> ſeemeth to imply</l>
                  <l>That, ſomewhat, which they aske he may deny.</l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:116005:16"/>
                  <l>And <hi>Reaſon</hi> ſayes, that none ſhould be confin'd</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Powr,</hi> to doe the work to him enjoyn'd;</l>
                  <l>Which, he would want, if of a <hi>Negative</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In ſuch like things as this, they him deprive.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I muſt confeſs, I ſtagger'd am, well neer,</l>
                  <l>And almoſt overawed with a fear</l>
                  <l>Of medling any further in this <hi>Point,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Leſt, I, may bring things farther out of <hi>joynt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That ſtand <hi>awry:</hi> for, I am not a ſtranger</l>
                  <l>To thoſe <hi>Concernments</hi> which it may endanger,</l>
                  <l>If, I, to common view, ſhould bring out that</l>
                  <l>Which is conceiv'd a <hi>Myſterie of State;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, ſhould intrench upon the <hi>Priviledges</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, due to <hi>Parliaments,</hi> this <hi>Nation</hi> judges:</l>
                  <l>Nor am I ignorant, what might to me</l>
                  <l>Thereby befall, ſhould I ſuſpected be,</l>
                  <l>(As it is ſomewhat probable I may)</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Arbitrary actings,</hi> to make way</l>
                  <l>Beyond due <hi>Limits</hi> (which, I doe abhor</l>
                  <l>With all my <hi>ſoul,</hi> to be a pleader for.)</l>
                  <l>Yet, I were falſe to <hi>truth,</hi> ſhould I not ſhew</l>
                  <l>What <hi>Tools</hi> are to his undertakings due,</l>
                  <l>Who muſt ſecure our <hi>Peace</hi> (becauſe he may</l>
                  <l>Make uſe of them perhaps another way.)</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Drunkard</hi> ſinneth by exceſs of <hi>Wine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet, we allow the planting of the <hi>Vine;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, I conceive it lawfull to expreſs</l>
                  <l>That, which may <hi>publique injuries</hi> redreſs,</l>
                  <l>Although it may occaſion ſome <hi>offence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which is of an <hi>inferiour conſequence.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I know, what to a <hi>Parliament</hi> hath been</l>
                  <l>Aſcrib'd; and, I have <hi>felt,</hi> as well as <hi>ſeen</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What <hi>powr</hi> it hath, and what that <hi>powr</hi> may do,</l>
                  <l>If, that exorbitance belongs thereto,</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:116005:17"/>
                  <l>Which many claim; and, which, it had obtain'd</l>
                  <l>Untill it was by <hi>Providence</hi> reſtrain'd.</l>
                  <l>It hath, to give it an <hi>enablement,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Peoples</hi> never failing <hi>Argument,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thereby, to make good, and oblige us to</l>
                  <l>What they are pleas'd we ſhould <hi>believe,</hi> or <hi>do:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ev'n this, (which oft doth puzzle and becumber</l>
                  <l>The <hi>wiſeſt men</hi>) an <hi>Over-voting Number.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It acts by <hi>Preſidents,</hi> which, may ſometimes</l>
                  <l>Make <hi>vertues</hi> to be puniſhed as <hi>crimes:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It takes a pow'r to make and unmake <hi>Treaſon;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To bind and looſe, as well our <hi>Faith</hi> as <hi>Reaſon;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To raiſe, or pull down <hi>Kings;</hi> from their <hi>poſſeſſions,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To throw men out; to puniſh for <hi>Tranſgreſſions,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Before there have been <hi>Law,</hi> to make them ſuch;</l>
                  <l>And, hath unto it ſelf aſſum'd ſo much,</l>
                  <l>That, doubtleſs, if there be no power in <hi>Him</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who ſhould be <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mpire,</hi> betwixt <hi>us</hi> and <hi>them,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To moderate (nor any other way</l>
                  <l>To qualifie) that which impoſe they may;</l>
                  <l>No <hi>ſingle Tyrant,</hi> now or heretofore,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Did,</hi> or can for the <hi>future,</hi> grieve us more,</l>
                  <l>Or more <hi>inſlave,</hi> then we our ſelves may do,</l>
                  <l>By means of thoſe whom we ſhall truſt unto:</l>
                  <l>Nor to ſo <hi>many</hi> can thoſe <hi>wrongs</hi> extend,</l>
                  <l>Nor be ſo hardly brought unto an <hi>end;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Conſid'ring, that, <hi>things preſent</hi> to enjoy,</l>
                  <l>Some, would their own <hi>poſterity</hi> deſtroy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We have had <hi>dear experience,</hi> both, long ſince,</l>
                  <l>And lately, what <hi>effects</hi> may flow from thence,</l>
                  <l>If, neither in our <hi>ſelves,</hi> nor in <hi>another,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor in <hi>them</hi> and a <hi>third pow'r,</hi> joyn'd together,</l>
                  <l>There may be means to ſave from what we fear;</l>
                  <l>Yea, we of our beſt <hi>hopes</hi> deprived are,</l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:116005:17"/>
                  <l>And have but leap'd (by ought that ſee I can)</l>
                  <l>Into the <hi>Fire,</hi> out of the <hi>Frying-pan:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, as <hi>things ſtand,</hi> when <hi>Deputies</hi> are choſe,</l>
                  <l>Whether, they be our <hi>faithfull friends,</hi> or <hi>foes;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whether, they have been <hi>well,</hi> or <hi>miſ-begotten;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whether, their <hi>Principles</hi> be ſound, or rotten;</l>
                  <l>Whether, they ſhall be <hi>Prudent,</hi> or <hi>unwiſe;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whether, their <hi>votes</hi> be gained by <hi>ſurprize,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or not; and, whether, that which they conclude</l>
                  <l>Be <hi>right</hi> or <hi>wrong;</hi> or, for our <hi>harm,</hi> or <hi>good,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>We have no remedy, but, muſt ſubmit</l>
                  <l>To whatſoever is adjudged fit:</l>
                  <l>And, not preſume to let a word be ſpoke</l>
                  <l>Againſt it, leſt their <hi>priviledge</hi> be broke.</l>
                  <l>But, ſure, there ſhould ſome <hi>bounds</hi> be ſet to <hi>them;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, I believe there is, by that <hi>Supreme</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Common law of Nature,</hi> which, in part</l>
                  <l>Is writ (though much defac'd) in every <hi>heart.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Therefore, that <hi>Law</hi> I very often read,</l>
                  <l>And, many times, for <hi>common freedoms</hi> plead,</l>
                  <l>As I finde <hi>cauſe;</hi> and, will not be afraid</l>
                  <l>To plead it, when aſide I ſee it laid,</l>
                  <l>Though I have <hi>blame;</hi> And, though, ſome wil ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>And ſay, <hi>Beyond his Laſt, this Cobler goes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>On that <hi>account,</hi> my <hi>Muſe</hi> compels me, here</l>
                  <l>To treat of things that ſeem beyond my <hi>Sphere;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, having for <hi>Affaires</hi> wherewith I deale</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Warrant</hi> in my boſome, under <hi>Seale,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I will proceed unto the <hi>point</hi> in hand,</l>
                  <l>So far forth as the ſame I underſtand:</l>
                  <l>For, that which is in queſtion, differs not</l>
                  <l>In what may follow, from the <hi>Gordian-knot;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, I ſhould grieve to ſee it <hi>knit</hi> ſo faſt,</l>
                  <l>That, by the <hi>Sword,</hi> it muſt be <hi>cut</hi> at laſt,</l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:116005:18"/>
                  <l>Or, all, thereby into a danger ſlide,</l>
                  <l>If ſtill, or overlong, it be <hi>unty'd.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I know not what this <hi>Parliament</hi> can doe,</l>
                  <l>Nor whether it be <hi>limited</hi> or no,</l>
                  <l>By him who called it: but, I believe,</l>
                  <l>It power with <hi>limitations</hi> did receive.</l>
                  <l>And, this I know; that, if there doth reſide</l>
                  <l>A <hi>pow'r</hi> therein, to force what is <hi>deny'd,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Maugre his <hi>Conſcience,</hi> who the ſame to ſave</l>
                  <l>From violence, doth one <hi>Propoſall</hi> wave;</l>
                  <l>I, thereupon conclude, it may as well</l>
                  <l>Againſt his <hi>ſingle-Reaſon,</hi> him compell;</l>
                  <l>And with more ſhew of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> if the ſtate</l>
                  <l>Of that, which is in queſtion, doth relate</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Civill things;</hi> becauſe, the <hi>reaſon</hi> ſhown</l>
                  <l>Is <hi>joyntly</hi> then, the <hi>peoples</hi> and his <hi>own,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They, being both his <hi>choſen Counſellors</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For ſuch <hi>affaires,</hi> and <hi>Deputies</hi> of theirs;</l>
                  <l>Who may as juſtly take his <hi>powr</hi> away</l>
                  <l>To <hi>morrow,</hi> as his <hi>Title,</hi> on <hi>this day,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Againſt his will; and, <hi>Him</hi> and <hi>His,</hi> expoſe</l>
                  <l>To all the rage and malice, of his <hi>foes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If, from conſtraint, his <hi>Conſcience</hi> be not free,</l>
                  <l>Sad will the <hi>conſequences</hi> thereof be.</l>
                  <l>If <hi>He,</hi> that <hi>freedom</hi> ſhall be barred from,</l>
                  <l>What of our <hi>Chriſtian freedoms</hi> will become?</l>
                  <l>Who as'tis thought, have given them a power</l>
                  <l>Without <hi>controule,</hi> to ſpare or to devoure,</l>
                  <l>As they ſhall pleaſe. But, ſure impowred thus</l>
                  <l>They never were by <hi>God,</hi> our <hi>Prince,</hi> or <hi>us,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By ought which <hi>tacitly</hi> did them inveſt</l>
                  <l>With ſuch powr; nor by any thing expreſt;</l>
                  <l>At leaſt <hi>de jure,</hi> though we are in <hi>Fact</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Concluded by thoſe <hi>Laws</hi> they ſhall enact.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:116005:18"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>For whatſoere the law of <hi>God</hi> or <hi>nature,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Confers upon the <hi>Reaſonable creature,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No <hi>Truſt,</hi> as <hi>Deputies</hi> of ours, have they</l>
                  <l>To meddle with (much leſs to take away)</l>
                  <l>Untill by thoſe <hi>Laws</hi> forfeited; unleſs</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Publique weale,</hi> or ſuccours in <hi>diſtreſs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For <hi>common ſafety.</hi> Nor then, have they <hi>pow'r</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O're <hi>perſon, freedom, goods,</hi> or ought that's our</l>
                  <l>In <hi>equity:</hi> unleſs, they alſo lay</l>
                  <l>As equally as poſſibly they may,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>burdens</hi> upon all; leſt, ſome beare <hi>nought,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As <hi>lately;</hi> and, ſome bee to <hi>ruin brought;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe prayres, cries, and vnredreſſed wrongs,</l>
                  <l>Is that which our <hi>Vnſetlement</hi> prolongs.</l>
                  <l>It wil be, therefore, our ſecureſt way,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Groundworke</hi> of our <hi>Government</hi> to lay</l>
                  <l>Vpon ſome <hi>Juſt Act,</hi> which may expiate</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>Sinnes</hi> that have committed been of late,</l>
                  <l>Through our defect of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Compaſſion,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To them who have beene faithfull to this Nation,</l>
                  <l>Ev'n to their owne undoing: were this done,</l>
                  <l>The works which now goe <hi>Backward,</hi> would <hi>goe on;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, <hi>God,</hi> would make us lovingly <hi>comply;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Inſtruct us what to <hi>Grant,</hi> or to deny.</l>
                  <l>Till this be done, we onely ſhall contrive</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Snares</hi> for each other; or, at beſt, but ſtrive</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Bees</hi> in hony-<hi>potts;</hi> and, be at laſt,</l>
                  <l>Deſtroy'd by that, in which our <hi>hopes</hi> are plaſt.</l>
                  <l>Yea, till theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> doe ſo conſtitute</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Parlaments,</hi> and them whom they <hi>Depute</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Obliges to <hi>fundamentals,</hi> they, ſhall never</l>
                  <l>Theire <hi>Liberties</hi> enjoy; but bee for ever</l>
                  <l>Expoſd to Hazzards (which might be prevented,</l>
                  <l>And none be therewith iuſtly diſcontented).</l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:116005:19"/>
                  <l>As now things are, at every <hi>Parlament,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May our <hi>Religion,</hi> or the <hi>Government,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Be innovated, to our greiſe or ſhame,</l>
                  <l>According to thoſe <hi>Modell,</hi> they will frame,</l>
                  <l>Who may by frau'd, or other manes uniuſt,</l>
                  <l>For ſuch end's, ſcrew into our <hi>Publike truſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sometimes, wee ſhall be govern'd by a <hi>king;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A few yeares after, by <hi>an other thing;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then, by <hi>a king</hi> againe; and, to all theſe</l>
                  <l>Be forced to engage, as others pleaſe;</l>
                  <l>With every <hi>wind,</hi> turn'd like a Weathercock,</l>
                  <l>Now faſt, now <hi>Looſe; out Nettle and in Dock;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yea, and to <hi>ſweare,</hi> till we may ſafely ſay</l>
                  <l>And <hi>ſweare,</hi> that, moſt have <hi>ſworn</hi> their <hi>faith</hi> away:</l>
                  <l>Which, to prevent, either from <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>him,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who, hath in all Affaires, the <hi>Pow'r Supreame</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our help muſt come; and, from a <hi>Parlament</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, thereunto ſhall give a full aſſent:</l>
                  <l>But, this can never be, (as I have ſaid</l>
                  <l>Elſewhere) until the <hi>Ground-worke</hi> be new laid;</l>
                  <l>And, till by good and perfect <hi>Chymeſtry,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Natures</hi> three <hi>principles, Salt, Mercury,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Sulphur,</hi> be to that juſt <hi>temprature,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſuch <hi>proportion</hi> brought, as will procure</l>
                  <l>To govern us, a <hi>Civil-Trinity,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Made up into a <hi>bleſſed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It ſelf (ſo far forth as it may be done)</l>
                  <l>Conforming to th' <hi>Eternall three-in-one</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Mercy.</hi> This product,</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>ſelfiſhneſs,</hi> doth hitherto obſtruct;</l>
                  <l>And wil, till <hi>God,</hi> in ſome things, hath a <hi>choice</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By <hi>Lot,</hi> when they are paſt by <hi>humane voice:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, much corruption that wil cure; and, then,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chriſts</hi> kingdom, will begin to be with men</l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:116005:19"/>
                  <l>More manifeſt; and, no <hi>falſe Chriſts</hi> appeare</l>
                  <l>As now, and heretofore, they have done here.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, know, that when a <hi>Government</hi> conſiſts</l>
                  <l>Of three <hi>Eſtates,</hi> 't will wrong thoſe <hi>Intereſts</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which to a <hi>Free Republicke</hi> do pertain,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs it be provided, that, thoſe <hi>twain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which are <hi>Superior,</hi> ſhall deſcend to none</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Birthright:</hi> But, that, thereto ev'ry one</l>
                  <l>Shall be elected; and, no perſon bear</l>
                  <l>Such <hi>Place,</hi> who was not born a <hi>Commoner;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, whoſe <hi>Poſterity,</hi> ſhall not return</l>
                  <l>To that <hi>Condition,</hi> whereto he was <hi>born.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, <hi>he,</hi> or <hi>his,</hi> will <hi>Tyrants</hi> be at laſt</l>
                  <l>By whom, this <hi>Propoſition</hi> is tranſgreſt.</l>
                  <l>Theſe things, perhaps, will come to paſs in time,</l>
                  <l>Whereof, I ſeem at preſent, but to dream;</l>
                  <l>And, peradventure, we till then, to gain</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Setlement,</hi> ſhall plodd, and ſtrive in vain.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Mean while, his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> or he, whoſoere</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>God,</hi> to the <hi>ſupream Office</hi> doth prefer,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Suffrage-negative,</hi> ſhould have in that,</l>
                  <l>Which, <hi>Publicke ſafty,</hi> doth neceſſitate</l>
                  <l>To be by him, or them, ſometime <hi>Denide:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By no means, can he otherwiſe provide</l>
                  <l>To keep his <hi>Honor,</hi> or, thoſe <hi>Dues,</hi> which muſt</l>
                  <l>Preſerve him able, to perform his <hi>truſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or bound them in their <hi>Orbe,</hi> who elſe, (as we</l>
                  <l>By proof have found) <hi>exorbitant</hi> may be,</l>
                  <l>And, like a <hi>Heard</hi> (if not well kept together)</l>
                  <l>When ſome <hi>break out,</hi> run all, they know not whether.</l>
                  <l>Nay, till there be a <hi>Gouvernment</hi> here fixt,</l>
                  <l>Things ballancing, ſo evenly, betwixt</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Prince, Peeres,</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> that, each may ſubſiſt,</l>
                  <l>And not infringe each others <hi>Intereſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:116005:20"/>
                  <l>He, that is our <hi>Supream,</hi> muſt truſted be</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Arbitray Power</hi> in ſome degree,</l>
                  <l>To carry on his <hi>work,</hi> and to ſecure</l>
                  <l>The <hi>whole,</hi> whilſt our <hi>unſettlements</hi> endure:</l>
                  <l>And, to effect that <hi>end,</hi> God did, perchance,</l>
                  <l>Deſtroy the <hi>Pow'r,</hi> that <hi>was;</hi> and this advance.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Without ſuch <hi>Pow'r</hi> a <hi>Prince</hi> choſe out of <hi>Logs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Like that which was beſtowed on the <hi>Frogs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Would be as good: <hi>Him,</hi> we might deal with all</l>
                  <l>As we ſhould pleaſe; and any thing might call,</l>
                  <l>And leap about him; till aſham'd we be</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch a <hi>Block,</hi> and chuſe a worſe then he.</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Parlament,</hi> hath done what <hi>them became</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>offrong;</hi> he, hath alſo done the ſame</l>
                  <l>In his <hi>refuſal:</hi> And, ſtill to adhere</l>
                  <l>To that whereof reſolv'd he doth appear,</l>
                  <l>Shall do <hi>as well,</hi> until <hi>that</hi> be removed</l>
                  <l>Which gives <hi>Offence,</hi> or, <hi>Inoffenſive</hi> proved:</l>
                  <l>And ſhould he be compelled to accept</l>
                  <l>Till that be done, <hi>Decorum</hi> were not kept.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They therefore, as I hope, will qualify</l>
                  <l>That, which he is inforced to <hi>deny,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(And thereby ſave the <hi>labour</hi> and the <hi>Coſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich, elſe, would in an <hi>evil time</hi> be loſt)</l>
                  <l>Rather then force him to an <hi>acceptation</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of that which would be an abomination</l>
                  <l>Both to <hi>himſelf</hi> and <hi>others:</hi> VVhich would prove</l>
                  <l>No Symptome of their <hi>Piety</hi> or <hi>Love:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, ſhould he be compelled unto that</l>
                  <l>VVhich moſt of his <hi>beſt Friends</hi> abominate,</l>
                  <l>And, his own <hi>Conſcience</hi> cheks at; It would give</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A Kingdom,</hi> which no wiſe man would receive;</l>
                  <l>And as it were inthrone him, (ſhall I tell</l>
                  <l>In plain termes where?) ev'n, in the Depths of <hi>Hell,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:116005:20"/>
                  <l>Within whoſe curſed bounds, is comprehended</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A wounded conſcience,</hi> wilfully offended.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is confeſt, the Title of a <hi>King</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is <hi>honorable,</hi> and may profit bring</l>
                  <l>To <hi>ſome who would conſerat;</hi> But, to <hi>Him</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No benefit (yea, and perhaps, to <hi>Them</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>At laſt as little) For, if he grow leſs</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Pow'r,</hi> that <hi>Title,</hi> will in his diſtreſs</l>
                  <l>Not ſo much <hi>help</hi> as <hi>hinder:</hi> And, then, <hi>they</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who gave it, will, firſt, take the ſame away:</l>
                  <l>Yea, if on <hi>that ſide</hi> an advantage grow,</l>
                  <l>They will beſtow it on his <hi>greateſt Foe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, if his <hi>Pow'r</hi> continue, he may ſtill</l>
                  <l>Support his <hi>Title,</hi> call him what you will;</l>
                  <l>And, that, to which none can lay claim but <hi>he,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Will <hi>ſafeſt</hi> upon all Adventures be.</l>
                  <l>Indeed, all things conſider'd well together,</l>
                  <l>There will be <hi>Hazards,</hi> both in <hi>th'one</hi> and <hi>th'other;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, <hi>leaſt</hi> in that, which will in proof be beſt</l>
                  <l>To keep that <hi>conſcience,</hi> which gives <hi>Inward reſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though, in it ſelf, we do confeſs the <hi>Title</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is honorable, it can add but little</l>
                  <l>To his <hi>Repute:</hi> Nay, it will be a blot</l>
                  <l>As things are, to that <hi>honour</hi> he hath got;</l>
                  <l>Which, if it ſeriouſly conſidered be,</l>
                  <l>Is of a higher nature and degree,</l>
                  <l>Than that which <hi>men confer;</hi> and, they ſhall do</l>
                  <l>No more who add a <hi>King-ſhip</hi> thereunto,</l>
                  <l>Than he, who <hi>Diamonds</hi> in <hi>Lead</hi> doth ſet,</l>
                  <l>Or, makes an <hi>Earl</hi> or <hi>Duke,</hi> a <hi>Baronet.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, <hi>Gideon,</hi> peradventure, did therefore</l>
                  <l>Refuſe a <hi>Kingſhip,</hi> being honour'd more</l>
                  <l>By what he was, then by what he thereby</l>
                  <l>Might have convey'd to his <hi>Poſterity.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:116005:21"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Kingſhip</hi> is <hi>lawful;</hi> yet, wiſe men do know</l>
                  <l>Things <hi>lawful,</hi> inexpedient ſometimes grow.</l>
                  <l>The Stile of <hi>King,</hi> was but an <hi>Ordination</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>men;</hi> and afterward by Toleration,</l>
                  <l>At their requeſt, by God himſelf allow'd</l>
                  <l>Unto his <hi>people</hi> (ſo, that neither proud</l>
                  <l>They did become, nor pufft up with ambition</l>
                  <l>O're others; which, thereof was one <hi>Condition.</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Yea, 'tis an Attribute of <hi>God,</hi> whereon</l>
                  <l>Was rais'd, this <hi>incommunicable one,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The King of Kings.</hi> If therefore, at the <hi>Name</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>We ſimply take offence, We are too blame:</l>
                  <l>Or, if we think, the Pow'r they give is leſs</l>
                  <l>Who, by <hi>Synonoma's,</hi> the ſame expreſs,</l>
                  <l>As many <hi>Nations</hi> do, who never had</l>
                  <l>A <hi>King</hi> among them, ſince the world was made,</l>
                  <l>Yet give their <hi>Princes</hi> pow'r, whereby they may</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rule well,</hi> and make their <hi>Subjects well obey.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Supream Perſon,</hi> always is the ſame</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Sover aignty,</hi> whatever him you <hi>name:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, they who do pretend, our <hi>Lawes</hi> to bring</l>
                  <l>Advantages, to him that's call'd a <hi>King</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which other <hi>Titles</hi> give not, do well know,</l>
                  <l>If, he be their <hi>Supream,</hi> it is not ſo:</l>
                  <l>For, ev'ry thing within our <hi>Lawes</hi> expreſt,</l>
                  <l>Wherein our former <hi>Kings</hi> had Intereſt,</l>
                  <l>Is virtually, ev'n by thoſe <hi>Lawes,</hi> deriv'd</l>
                  <l>To him, who for our <hi>Soveraign</hi> is receiv'd.</l>
                  <l>And, whatſoever they make ſhew of, may,</l>
                  <l>Who make the <hi>Law,</hi> ſpeak what they pleaſe to ſay,</l>
                  <l>Were that, which is now conquerd by our <hi>Swords,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Brought to their <hi>Bars,</hi> to be new tri'd by <hi>Words,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Judgment</hi> would be given on that ſide</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Pow'r,</hi> not where the <hi>Kingſhip</hi> did reſide,</l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:116005:21"/>
                  <l>Although the <hi>Law</hi> ſpoke for it, and forbad</l>
                  <l>All other <hi>Governments:</hi> For, <hi>Laws</hi> are made</l>
                  <l>To ſpeak, too often, not to that <hi>good end</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For which, <hi>Law-makers,</hi> did them firſt intend:</l>
                  <l>But, what beſt makes out their <hi>Accommodation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who take upon them their Interpretation.</l>
                  <l>Elſe, they could tell you (without my direction)</l>
                  <l>That, he, whom <hi>God</hi> hath rais'd for our Protection,</l>
                  <l>Had for his <hi>Church,</hi> and for his <hi>Common-weal,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Pow'r</hi> he owns, confirm'd on that <hi>Appeal</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They made to <hi>God,</hi> when that, for which they fought,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Trial,</hi> in an <hi>Open Field,</hi> was brought.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> is by our <hi>Law,</hi> the utmoſt <hi>Trial</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That can be had: and <hi>He,</hi> (without denial)</l>
                  <l>And his <hi>Adheres,</hi> have right in that reſpect,</l>
                  <l>To any <hi>Title</hi> which they will elect:</l>
                  <l>Yea, and may <hi>Change, Confirm,</hi> or make the <hi>Lawes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Such, as their <hi>Safety,</hi> and the <hi>Common Cauſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall now require: Provided, it accord</l>
                  <l>With their <hi>Truſt,</hi> for whoſe ſake they drew the <hi>Sword;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And with thoſe ancient Rights, by <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Conferr'd upon the <hi>Reaſonable Creature:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, if they ſhall invade, their <hi>Swords</hi> now worn,</l>
                  <l>Upon <hi>Themſelves,</hi> juſt vengeance will return:</l>
                  <l>For, that <hi>Pow'r,</hi> was conferred to provide</l>
                  <l>A form of <hi>Government</hi> ſo rectifide,</l>
                  <l>That, neither <hi>Prince,</hi> nor <hi>Peers,</hi> nor <hi>People</hi> might</l>
                  <l>Intrench, hereafter, on each others <hi>Right:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yea, (that by what <hi>ſhall be,</hi> and what is <hi>paſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>God's</hi> purpoſe might be manifeſt, at laſt)</l>
                  <l>It them impowers, to lay down thoſe <hi>Foundations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That ſhall by <hi>This,</hi> and future <hi>Generations</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Be <hi>built</hi> upon: In which <hi>work,</hi> if they ſhould</l>
                  <l>Leave any <hi>Arch,</hi> or <hi>Pillars,</hi> rais'd of old,</l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:116005:22"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Miſ-laid,</hi> or <hi>Crooked, Rotten,</hi> or <hi>Miſ-wrought,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It would, at laſt, bring all the Pile to nought.</l>
                  <l>And therefore, to this <hi>end,</hi> oblig'd they are</l>
                  <l>Touſe their <hi>Pow'r</hi> with <hi>Prudency</hi> and care.</l>
                  <l>To this <hi>end, Providence,</hi> into their hands</l>
                  <l>Let that <hi>Pow'r</hi> ſlip, which at this day commands;</l>
                  <l>And they, who meerly for their own ends uſe it,</l>
                  <l>Are <hi>Tyrants,</hi> or elſe <hi>Traitors,</hi> and abuſe it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That, which may of <hi>Protectorſhip</hi> be ſaid,</l>
                  <l>Was, long ago, made publique to be weigh'd;</l>
                  <l>(Not without cauſe, although to many men,</l>
                  <l>It ſeemed an Impertinency, then)</l>
                  <l>And, as if that had been <hi>foreſeen,</hi> which would</l>
                  <l>Be <hi>offer'd</hi> now, the <hi>Sequel</hi> was foretold,</l>
                  <l>Which would enſue on changing of that <hi>Title,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With other things regarded but a little;</l>
                  <l>Which, to repeat here, were but (in effect)</l>
                  <l>To offer them again to your neglect.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>New Titles,</hi> future <hi>Grandeur,</hi> do foreſhew;</l>
                  <l>The <hi>greateſt Titles,</hi> at the firſt were <hi>New:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, though the <hi>Government</hi> which we yet have,</l>
                  <l>Was only modellized, but to ſave</l>
                  <l>From likely ruine, till we <hi>ſtrongth</hi> ſhould get</l>
                  <l>To raiſe up <hi>that,</hi> which might be more compleat;</l>
                  <l>You, in this <hi>Title</hi> no defect can ſee,</l>
                  <l>If, but <hi>Imperial</hi> thereto added be,</l>
                  <l>Or, ſomewhat elſe, to put a <hi>difference</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Twixt <hi>This,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> in <hi>Nonage</hi> of a <hi>Prince:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, thoſe additions which do not eſtrange,</l>
                  <l>But help <hi>explain a Title,</hi> are no change.</l>
                  <l>What, if his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> doth ſuppoſe it given</l>
                  <l>(As I believe) by <hi>Providence</hi> from Heaven?</l>
                  <l>And thinks <hi>Himſelf</hi> engag'd, not to neglect</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Gift?</hi> And what, if for the like reſpect,</l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:116005:22"/>
                  <l>His <hi>Friends</hi> conceiv'd it might be <hi>Ominous,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Either to <hi>Him who owns</hi> it, or to <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Without an urgent cauſe to change the ſame</l>
                  <l>For <hi>King,</hi> or any other <hi>Soveraign Name?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Should this great <hi>Title</hi> be rejected for</l>
                  <l>That, which his <hi>beſt affected Friends</hi> abhor?</l>
                  <l>And, they, thereby grow jealous, that his <hi>heart</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Which ſeem'd inclined to the better part)</l>
                  <l>Had left it for the <hi>world,</hi> and for thoſe <hi>toyes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Wherein her <hi>fooliſh Favourites</hi> rejoyce?</l>
                  <l>Might not thereon, ſome <hi>Conſequence</hi> enſue,</l>
                  <l>Which, peradventure, <hi>He,</hi> or <hi>We,</hi> might rue?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What, if <hi>God</hi> gave that <hi>Title</hi> for a <hi>Teſt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of his adherence to that Intereſt,</l>
                  <l>Which doth concern Chriſts <hi>Kingdom?</hi> and to ſhow</l>
                  <l>That if what God conferr'd he ſhall forgoe</l>
                  <l>(For what the <hi>World</hi> will offer) he beſt prizes</l>
                  <l>The things of this <hi>World,</hi> and his <hi>Grace</hi> deſpiſes?</l>
                  <l>Or what, (if as that <hi>Blood,</hi> which heretofore</l>
                  <l>Sprinkled the <hi>Poſts,</hi> and <hi>Lintels</hi> of the doore)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>God,</hi> gave this <hi>Title</hi> for a difference</l>
                  <l>Betwixt the <hi>Kings of Babel,</hi> and his <hi>Prince?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That he may be ſecur'd, when to deſtroy</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chriſts</hi> foes, he ſhall that <hi>Army</hi> here imploy,</l>
                  <l>Which will caſt out their <hi>fleſh,</hi> to <hi>Beaſts</hi> and <hi>Fowls,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To <hi>Devils,</hi> give their miſerable <hi>ſouls?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Make, that abominable <hi>Scarlet-Whore</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Their <hi>painted Miſtreſs.</hi> deſolate and poor?</l>
                  <l>And, throw them irrecoverably thither,</l>
                  <l>Where, they ſhall burn perpetually together?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This</hi> may be; for, the time is drawing on</l>
                  <l>Wherein, ſuch <hi>Executions</hi> will be done.</l>
                  <l>And therefore, in his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> it implies</l>
                  <l>Much <hi>Chriſtian Prudency,</hi> that he denies</l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:116005:23"/>
                  <l>What's offred now; and, he ſhall be innobl'd</l>
                  <l>Much more thereby, then by thoſe <hi>Offers</hi> doubl'd,</l>
                  <l>If he perſiſt; <hi>Clear Symptoms,</hi> he hath given</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>good events,</hi> by having ſo long ſtriven</l>
                  <l>Againſt what, ſeemingly, doth offer him</l>
                  <l>Things, of moſt value in the <hi>worlds</hi> eſteem:</l>
                  <l>For, they infer, that he is rais'd above</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Sphere,</hi> who on ſuch objects ſet their love;</l>
                  <l>That, his <hi>Promotions,</hi> he expects not from</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Eaſt</hi> or <hi>Weſt;</hi> nor cares for thoſe that come</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Oblique Winds:</hi> But, moſt account doth make</l>
                  <l>Of what the <hi>World,</hi> can neither <hi>give</hi> nor <hi>take.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>Outward Trappings,</hi> which make ſo much ſhow</l>
                  <l>Of what theſe <hi>Nations</hi> do on him beſtow,</l>
                  <l>Are not on him beſtown, but, on the <hi>State.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The great <hi>Allowances,</hi> much murmur'd at,</l>
                  <l>Are upon him conferr'd, for their <hi>own ſakes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ev'n to ſecure <hi>Themſelves:</hi> And, them he takes</l>
                  <l>For that intent; becauſe, thereby, he muſt,</l>
                  <l>And cannot otherwiſe, perform his <hi>Truſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whereas, if he perceiv'd it would as little</l>
                  <l>Secure the <hi>Publike,</hi> as their <hi>Offer'd Title,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, on his <hi>Conſcience</hi> preſs, as that will do,</l>
                  <l>I, do believe, he would refuſe <hi>that,</hi> too.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Preſume I may not, to declare to thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who are in <hi>Pow'r,</hi> which way, they might compoſe</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Diffrences;</hi> nor have I ought to ſay,</l>
                  <l>To that <hi>End,</hi> which, I warrantably may</l>
                  <l>Propound: For, if I had, neither the <hi>fear</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of thoſe <hi>Wits,</hi> who, take liberty to <hi>jeer,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>worſe things,</hi> could affright me; I, have told</l>
                  <l>As much, as I can <hi>ſeaſonably</hi> unfold:</l>
                  <l>Except this <hi>Hint</hi> that follows, doth conduce</l>
                  <l>To ſomewhat, which, may ſafely be of uſe.</l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:116005:23"/>
                  <l>Perhaps, it is <hi>Caſt in,</hi> but to <hi>Inſnare;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Perhaps, to make proof, how <hi>inclined you are.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Be wary, therefore, how far you <hi>proceed</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Therein; and mind, I warn'd you, to <hi>Take heed.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Should it offend, I dare not change a <hi>Line;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, though <hi>I ſpeak,</hi> theſe <hi>Arrands</hi> are not mine.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>God,</hi> ſets before us, <hi>this,</hi> and <hi>that,</hi> to chuſe,</l>
                  <l>And leav's us free, to <hi>Take</hi> or to <hi>Refuſe;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, ſuch <hi>markes</hi> gives, of what may prove amiſs,</l>
                  <l>That, if we chuſe not well, the fault's not <hi>His.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They, who ſincerely think, the Stile of <hi>King</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Will to this <hi>Commonwealth</hi> advantage bring;</l>
                  <l>And, they, who fear it would portend no good</l>
                  <l>The title of <hi>Protector</hi> to explode,</l>
                  <l>May, if they can agree, joyn them together,</l>
                  <l>And pleaſe perhaps, both <hi>Parties;</hi> perhaps, <hi>neither,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Till ſomewhat reconcile them, which, <hi>fit Seaſon</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>More likely ſeems to bring to paſs then <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe <hi>Titles</hi> are <hi>conſiſtent;</hi> and, if that</l>
                  <l>Which is <hi>refus'd,</hi> be made <hi>Subordinate,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And this <hi>Supream;</hi> that it may thereunto</l>
                  <l>Be <hi>Vaſſal,</hi> and a kind of <hi>Homage</hi> do,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>conquered;</hi> it might be ſerviceable</l>
                  <l>With leſs offence, (for ought that I am able</l>
                  <l>To counterſay:) for, that wiſe <hi>Legiſlator</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who was preſerv'd, by <hi>Ruſhes,</hi> from the water,</l>
                  <l>Was call'd a <hi>King;</hi> and, therewith had the <hi>Pow'r</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, conſtitutes with us, an <hi>Emperor,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And in that <hi>Commonwealth</hi> (which was the beſt)</l>
                  <l>Both <hi>Kingly,</hi> and <hi>Imperial Pow'r</hi> poſſeſt;</l>
                  <l>Which, if confer'd on him, who governs us,</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Title,</hi> might be then contrived thus,</l>
                  <l>Or, ſome ſuch way: On <hi>feet,</hi> in <hi>Verſe,</hi> it goes</l>
                  <l>But lamely; Therefore, take it here, in <hi>Proſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:116005:24"/>
               <q>
                  <hi>Soveraign Protector,</hi> or, <hi>Protector Imperial</hi> of the Commonwealth of <hi>Great Brittain,</hi> King of England, Scotland, and Ireland, with the Iſlands, Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Dominions, to them belonging.</q>
               <lg>
                  <l>This, is not <hi>Magiſterially</hi> propos'd,</l>
                  <l>As if thereby all <hi>Ruptures</hi> would be clos'd;</l>
                  <l>Nor is it my deſire, it ſhould <hi>ſo be,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, <hi>not be ſo;</hi> for, it concernes not me.</l>
                  <l>It, almoſt, into <hi>words</hi> was thus far brought,</l>
                  <l>E're it was fully formed in my thought;</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>ſlipt out,</hi> (as do ſuch things now and then)</l>
                  <l>Rather, to try the <hi>mindes of other men,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then to declare my <hi>Judgment;</hi> which, I give,</l>
                  <l>(VVhen I intend ſo) in <hi>terms poſitive.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, thus much, I will ſay; <hi>This</hi> is by none</l>
                  <l>Yet <hi>claymed;</hi> neither gives to any one</l>
                  <l>Juſt cauſe of <hi>Quarrel: Honourable Pow'r</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Holds forth: Is, by the <hi>Law of Conqueſt</hi> our,</l>
                  <l>And, may within our own <hi>Realmes,</hi> be aſſum'd,</l>
                  <l>Yet, nothing be undecently preſum'd,</l>
                  <l>If we, know by what means, to limite ſo</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Pow'r,</hi> which therewith all, we ſhall beſtow,</l>
                  <l>That no offence it gives; nor may produce</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pride, Folly,</hi> or <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> by abuſe.</l>
                  <l>But, what would follow, ſhould this fanci'd be,</l>
                  <l>It is not in my dim ſight, to foreſee;</l>
                  <l>And therefore, to be weigh'd by thoſe, I leave it,</l>
                  <l>VVhom it concernes to <hi>Offer,</hi> &amp; <hi>Receive it:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To whom (if ſought where ſuch things may be known)</l>
                  <l>It ſhall be, to their ſatisfaction ſhown,</l>
                  <l>How far <hi>this,</hi> or the <hi>Title</hi> of a <hi>King</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May be aſſum'd, and no diſturbance bring.</l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:116005:24"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Powr,</hi> though <hi>bred Tame,</hi> is an <hi>unruly beaſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which if it feed much on <hi>ſelfe intereſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Growes quickly <hi>wild;</hi> and every thing commands</l>
                  <l>Except it <hi>ſelfe;</hi> yea breaks the <hi>ſtrongeſt Bands,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which once caſt off, <hi>Reſtraint</hi> it will avoyd,</l>
                  <l>And never more be bound, till 'tis deſtroyd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our beſt <hi>courſe</hi> therefore is not to be ſtrugling</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Powr</hi> (Although it ſeems upheld by <hi>Jugling</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As well as by <hi>good meanes</hi>) or to contend</l>
                  <l>With things <hi>without us,</hi> which <hi>War</hi> hath no end:</l>
                  <l>But rather to compoſe and order ſo</l>
                  <l>All things <hi>within us,</hi> as we ought to do:</l>
                  <l>For, there we may have <hi>Peace</hi> (when we have done</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Duties</hi>) In <hi>externals,</hi> there is none:</l>
                  <l>And what we get by <hi>Politick Contrivings</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By <hi>Falſhood, Force, Diſſembling,</hi> or <hi>Connivings,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Doth for the moſt part, but the more diſorder</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>mindes;</hi> and from our <hi>hopes</hi> divide us further.</l>
                  <l>Yea, whether our <hi>cheife Magiſtrate,</hi> we ſhall</l>
                  <l>A <hi>King</hi> hereafter, or <hi>Protector</hi> call,</l>
                  <l>'Twill not be much materiall, what the <hi>Name</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall be, if all things elſe be ſtill the ſame.</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>His,</hi> nor <hi>our condition</hi> will be betterd</l>
                  <l>Whilſt we are with thoſe <hi>Vanities</hi> befetterd,</l>
                  <l>Which to <hi>caſt off,</hi> we lately made a <hi>ſhew:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, whilſt in <hi>ſecret,</hi> we do ſtill purſue</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>old wayes,</hi> and continue, in <hi>effect,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What we in <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> do reject.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Some are perſwaded, that the ſtile of <hi>King</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May be as well aſſumed, as that <hi>Thing</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which gives like <hi>Power:</hi> And ſo it may, if he</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Jehu,</hi> or a <hi>Jeroboam</hi> be,</l>
                  <l>Who, neither conſcience makes whom he offend;</l>
                  <l>Or ſcandalizeth, to obtaine his <hi>Ends;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:116005:25"/>
                  <l>Or if he uſe that <hi>Power,</hi> which is beſtowne</l>
                  <l>For <hi>publick workes,</hi> to bring to paſſe his <hi>owne.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, howſoever, let it be our care</l>
                  <l>Still to performe what our <hi>Obligements</hi> are:</l>
                  <l>Which are not to engage him unto <hi>On<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Offence,</hi> through fear another may be done:</l>
                  <l>Or, to reſiſt the <hi>Power</hi> we ſhould obey</l>
                  <l>Becauſe it ſeems by an <hi>unlawfull way</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Acquir'd or kept: For, every <hi>Wiſe man</hi> knows</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Powr, Thrones,</hi> and <hi>Glorie,</hi> are at GOD's diſpoſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is by other ſome not meanly fear'd,</l>
                  <l>Such <hi>Powr</hi> is by <hi>Protectorſhip</hi> conferd,</l>
                  <l>That he may now infring our <hi>freedomes</hi> more</l>
                  <l>Then any of our <hi>Princes</hi> heretofore:</l>
                  <l>Which may be likewiſe true; yet, what GOD gave</l>
                  <l>Wherewith to do him <hi>ſervice,</hi> he muſt have</l>
                  <l>To whom he gives it; If he then abuſe it,</l>
                  <l>To their <hi>wrong,</hi> for whoſe <hi>well-fare</hi> he ſhould uſe it,</l>
                  <l>GOD will aveng it: And though he defers</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Vengance,</hi> (and the <hi>Polititian</hi> Jeers</l>
                  <l>At ſuch a <hi>Vindication</hi>) 'twill be paid</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Intereſt,</hi> for all the time delay'd,</l>
                  <l>As ſoone as our <hi>Repentance,</hi> and thoſe <hi>wrongs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are for <hi>that</hi> ripened, which to them belongs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> and their <hi>Parlaments,</hi> talk much</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Freedomes,</hi> as if ſuch</l>
                  <l>To them pertained, now, as they have had.</l>
                  <l>Indeed, there is an <hi>Image</hi> of them made,</l>
                  <l>Whereby, we, them a little honor'd ſee</l>
                  <l>Before the <hi>People,</hi> (as <hi>Saul</hi> ſought to be.)</l>
                  <l>But, of thoſe <hi>Priviledges,</hi> we have none;</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Glorie</hi> is departed; they are gone:</l>
                  <l>We, by no <hi>tenure,</hi> any claime can lay</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Courteſie of England,</hi> at this day,</l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:116005:25"/>
                  <l>To what, by <hi>Birth</hi> was ours; or unto ought</l>
                  <l>Which we have <hi>purchaſ'd,</hi> or for which we <hi>ſought:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And till our <hi>ſupream Magiſtrate</hi> repaires</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Loſſes;</hi> Or, till GOD ſhall hear our Prayers</l>
                  <l>And <hi>cries</hi> (if he oppreſſe us) we ſhall ſtill</l>
                  <l>No other be, but, <hi>Tenants at his Will.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet is not he in fault; nor is our <hi>Caſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So bad, or in ſuch hazzard as it was.</l>
                  <l>For, if it were not ſo, it might be worſe;</l>
                  <l>And, that which we ſuppoſe to be a <hi>Curſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May prove a <hi>Bleſſing.</hi> Otherwhile, men loſe</l>
                  <l>By having all things at their owne diſpoſe;</l>
                  <l>And ſometimes <hi>gaine</hi> by <hi>looſing.</hi> what was our,</l>
                  <l>Did lately ſlip into anothers <hi>pow'r;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who, thereof taketh (by that <hi>forfeiture</hi>)</l>
                  <l>But ſo much, as our <hi>Freedomes</hi> may ſecure</l>
                  <l>To us hereafter. VVhen, he ſeems to <hi>wound</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He doth but lance a <hi>ſoare,</hi> to make that ſound</l>
                  <l>Which would deſtroy us: when, unto ſome <hi>coſt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He puts us, 'tis that <hi>all</hi> may not be loſt.</l>
                  <l>Yea, for our <hi>well-fare,</hi> he is <hi>meanes</hi> contriving,</l>
                  <l>When we moſt wrong him, by a <hi>miſbeleeving.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And doth diſcharge his <hi>Truſt</hi> (as I beleeve)</l>
                  <l>By doing that, whereof we miſconceive.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though he permits us to capitulate</l>
                  <l>With <hi>him,</hi> as it we did participate</l>
                  <l>In his <hi>Powr;</hi> ſuff'ring us to <hi>claime</hi> and <hi>take</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>Priviledges,</hi> whereby he may make</l>
                  <l>An <hi>advantageous uſe,</hi> with leaſt offence,</l>
                  <l>To bring to paſſe the <hi>work</hi> of <hi>Providence;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And to ſuch <hi>purpoſes,</hi> is well content</l>
                  <l>To all our <hi>juſt requeſts,</hi> to give aſſent:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thoſe things,</hi> do not to us of <hi>right</hi> pertain;</l>
                  <l>They are meer <hi>Acts of Favor;</hi> no <hi>remain</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:116005:26"/>
                  <l>Of our old <hi>freedomes:</hi> And, 'twill hazzardize</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Reſtauration,</hi> to think otherwiſe:</l>
                  <l>For, thoſe <hi>Thoughts</hi> hindring that compleat <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which GOD requires, will hinder their fruition,</l>
                  <l>By making us, perhaps, that <hi>meanes</hi> endeavor</l>
                  <l>To <hi>gain them,</hi> which will <hi>loſe them,</hi> quite, for ever.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In <hi>provocations,</hi> IS'RAEL did proceed</l>
                  <l>So far, that thereupon GOD had decreed</l>
                  <l>No <hi>Ranſome from</hi> deſtruction ſhould redeem</l>
                  <l>Their glorious <hi>Temple</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, their <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> to a <hi>forraigne King.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>On <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> for our tranſgreſſions, GOD doth bring</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Judgment</hi> ſomewhat like it: And, before</l>
                  <l>He, will to us our <hi>Liberties</hi> reſtore,</l>
                  <l>We muſt quite loſe them, and ſubmit to <hi>Him</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whome, as (in that reſpect) we did contemn.</l>
                  <l>And, now, no <hi>humane Policy,</hi> or <hi>Force</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Can put us into any likely <hi>Courſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of repoſſeſſing them, ſave that <hi>Compliance,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVith which we have been long time at <hi>defiance;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, whereto he that ſhould adviſe, might ſpeed</l>
                  <l>As bad, perhaps, as <hi>Jeremiah</hi> did</l>
                  <l>VVhen he in vaine, his <hi>Countrymen</hi> perſwaded</l>
                  <l>To fly to <hi>him,</hi> who had their Land invaded.</l>
                  <l>But, ſo it <hi>muſt be;</hi> and, if to <hi>beleeve</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhat <hi>muſt be,</hi> may aſſurance thereof give.</l>
                  <l>Or, if things probable in <hi>Reaſon,</hi> may</l>
                  <l>Confirme that, which I now <hi>beleeve</hi> and <hi>ſay,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our much <hi>averſeneſſe,</hi> rather will bring on</l>
                  <l>Then hinder, that which muſt at laſt be done.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, we are torne into ſo many <hi>fractions,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Growne of ſo many <hi>mindes,</hi> by our <hi>diſtractions,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Or <hi>Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eractings)</hi> ev'ry <hi>Party</hi> ſtriving</l>
                  <l>To bring to paſſe things of their own <hi>contriving,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:116005:26"/>
                  <l>Al men ſo apt, whom <hi>place of truſt,</hi> enable</l>
                  <l>For their owne <hi>private ends,</hi> to ſcrape and ſcrable;</l>
                  <l>And every man ſo jealous, and affraid,</l>
                  <l>Of being to his <hi>Oppoſite</hi> betray'd;</l>
                  <l>That, (as <hi>the World</hi> was, when it firſt begun)</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> muſt be the <hi>work</hi> of <hi>One;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e,</hi> that hath <hi>Powr,</hi> and, in <hi>whome,</hi> to agree</l>
                  <l>They, who are moſt concernd, moſt likely be.</l>
                  <l>This One, GOD, hath provided to reſtore</l>
                  <l>All, that our <hi>Kings</hi> uſurped heretofore</l>
                  <l>(Or, our Sins forfeited) And to reſetle</l>
                  <l>On us, thoſe <hi>bleſſings,</hi> by a <hi>ſtronger Title;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(If neither <hi>He,</hi> nor theſe divided <hi>Nations</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall, willfully, make fruſtrate their <hi>Probations</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Though, many are, yet, fearfull that he may</l>
                  <l>In ſome things, act the quite <hi>centrary way.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>Counſels,</hi> he hath oft together brought</l>
                  <l>VVhich we in <hi>former times,</hi> moſt proper thought</l>
                  <l>For ſuch a <hi>Worke;</hi> and, much hath taken in,</l>
                  <l>VVhich offerd, by ſome <hi>private hands,</hi> hath been,</l>
                  <l>But, both their <hi>Ends,</hi> and <hi>Contributions</hi> are</l>
                  <l>So diffring, and from <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitie</hi> ſo far;</l>
                  <l>That, what he hath deſired ſhould be done,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Leſſe perfect</hi> ſeems, then when it was begun.</l>
                  <l>And 'tis not poſſible their <hi>work</hi> ſhould be</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Long-laſting,</hi> who, in ſo few things agree.</l>
                  <l>He, therefore (as in all times paſt, we finde</l>
                  <l>It hath been done) who, is by GOD deſignd</l>
                  <l>To change a <hi>Government;</hi> and, unto <hi>whome</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He alwayes, an <hi>Aſſiſtant</hi> will become,</l>
                  <l>For his <hi>owne works;</hi> that <hi>ſpirit,</hi> muſt improve</l>
                  <l>VVhich GOD on him conferreth to promove</l>
                  <l>His <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakeings.</hi> Then, <hi>reſolve</hi> he muſt</l>
                  <l>On what his <hi>Conſcience</hi> judgeth to be juſt,</l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:116005:27"/>
                  <l>And by his <hi>Pow'r</hi> confirm it: elſe, the <hi>Waies</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Now follow'd, will deſtroy him, by <hi>Delayes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By this <hi>Courſe,</hi> and by weighing well thoſe things</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>faithfull men,</hi> and his <hi>experience</hi> brings</l>
                  <l>To be <hi>conſider'd,</hi> he <hi>himſelfe,</hi> alone,</l>
                  <l>Shall do that, which will never, elſe be done;</l>
                  <l>Even he alone, if, he, himſelf deny</l>
                  <l>(And on that <hi>wiſdome,</hi> and that <hi>pow'r</hi> rely,</l>
                  <l>Which hitherto, hath carried him along)</l>
                  <l>Shall, for his <hi>undertakings,</hi> be more ſtrong</l>
                  <l>Then, if he were with all the <hi>ſtrength,</hi> ſupplyd</l>
                  <l>And all the <hi>wiſdome,</hi> of the <hi>world</hi> beſide;</l>
                  <l>For, that ſhall teach him, what <hi>adviſe</hi> to chuſe:</l>
                  <l>What he muſt alter, what he muſt refuſe,</l>
                  <l>And what to fix upon: which, will be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ore</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Honour,</hi> then his <hi>Conqueſts</hi> heretofore;</l>
                  <l>Or, then to leave through <hi>future Generations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>Kingſhip</hi> to his ſeed, o're many <hi>Nations.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This done; a <hi>Parlament</hi> well conſtituted</l>
                  <l>Will crown the work: then, ſuch as are reputed</l>
                  <l>Juſt <hi>Priviledges,</hi> will be all reſtord;</l>
                  <l>Then, they, who now <hi>agree not,</hi> will <hi>accord:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then, will our <hi>Lawes,</hi> which yet are made a <hi>Snare,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Have thoſe effects, for which ordaind they were,</l>
                  <l>And, other things, be fairly carried on</l>
                  <l>VVhich, now, in crooked muddy <hi>Chanels</hi> run.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVee, in this <hi>worke</hi> of <hi>Providence,</hi> moſt heed</l>
                  <l>Thoſe groſſe, and oblique <hi>Actings,</hi> which proceed</l>
                  <l>From mans corruption; and, the deeds of thoſe</l>
                  <l>Whom for <hi>falſe friends,</hi> or elſe, for <hi>Open foes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVee do ſuſpect; and, greatly vexed are</l>
                  <l>VVith thoſe <hi>miſactings,</hi> which, in them appear;</l>
                  <l>As if, their <hi>failings only,</hi> were occaſions</l>
                  <l>Of all our <hi>loſſes,</hi> and our <hi>Preturbations;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:116005:27"/>
                  <l>But, were it well obſerved, we ſhould find</l>
                  <l>That, thoſe <hi>grand-works,</hi> which are by GOD deſign'd,</l>
                  <l>Are no leſſe further'd, by our <hi>overſights,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our <hi>weaknes, follies,</hi> and our foes <hi>deſpights,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then by our <hi>Virtues, Prudency,</hi> or <hi>Powr,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, any <hi>ſuffrings,</hi> or <hi>good deeds</hi> of our;</l>
                  <l>And, thereupon, prepare <hi>a way</hi> for <hi>Peace,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By prizing <hi>others</hi> more, and, our <hi>ſelves</hi> leſſe.</l>
                  <l>Or, if our <hi>Intellectuall eyes</hi> could ſee</l>
                  <l>VVhat GOD hath done, or, what thoſe actings be</l>
                  <l>VVhereby, his <hi>finger,</hi> doth make manifeſt</l>
                  <l>VVhat <hi>changes,</hi> have infringd our <hi>intereſt;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVe, in true <hi>meekneſſe,</hi> would incline unto</l>
                  <l>VVhat he expects, we, ſhould <hi>beleeve</hi> and <hi>do;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then, we ſhould finde, thoſe <hi>changes</hi> were permitted</l>
                  <l>That, for GOD's, <hi>work</hi> we might be better fitted;</l>
                  <l>That, his great <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> might be known;</l>
                  <l>That, our great <hi>failings,</hi> we, might <hi>know,</hi> and <hi>owne;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, it might give us many <hi>Evidences</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How little truſt there is, in <hi>earthly Princes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>Parlaments,</hi> or, in the beſt of thoſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Externall things,</hi> wherein we <hi>truſt</hi> repoſe:</l>
                  <l>And, that, we thence may learne, when we have tride</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Truſtleſneſſe,</hi> in whome, we ſhould confide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As ſure</hi> as, GOD, ten tribes from <hi>David</hi> rent,</l>
                  <l>And, made <hi>Belſhazers</hi> doome, a preſident</l>
                  <l>For <hi>future times</hi> to heed; and, tooke from <hi>Saul</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And other <hi>Kings</hi> thoſe <hi>Kingdomes</hi> wherewith al</l>
                  <l>They were indowd: <hi>ſo ſurely,</hi> was the <hi>Throne</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of our preceding <hi>King,</hi> by GOD, broke down:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So ſurely,</hi> he, who now inthroned ſits,</l>
                  <l>VVas raiſd by <hi>him;</hi> and, that if he forgets</l>
                  <l>On what <hi>Conditions,</hi> he, that grace received,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So ſurely,</hi> ſhall he be againe deprived,</l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:116005:28"/>
                  <l>Of what he yet injoyes; and be devour'd</l>
                  <l>By that, whereby, he was at firſt impowr'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As ſure,</hi> as <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſons delivered were</l>
                  <l>Into the hands of <hi>Nabuchadnezer,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Eglon, Jabin, Siſera,</hi> and thoſe</l>
                  <l>VVho, did on them great <hi>Slaveries</hi> impoſe;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So certainly,</hi> did GOD give up theſe <hi>Lands</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In former times, into <hi>Oppreſſors</hi> hands,</l>
                  <l>Both <hi>Temporall,</hi> and <hi>Ghoſtly;</hi> cauſing them</l>
                  <l>In various wiſe, to be from time to time,</l>
                  <l>Either <hi>afflicted, eaſ'd, inthrall'd</hi> or <hi>freed</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As to do <hi>well,</hi> or <hi>ill,</hi> they did proceed:</l>
                  <l>And, lately, hath powr'd forth his <hi>vials</hi> here</l>
                  <l>On <hi>Preiſt</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> upon <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Peer;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet, if we grow not better than we be,</l>
                  <l>Far ſadder <hi>Changes,</hi> we may live to ſee,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe, ſuch <hi>Provocations,</hi> ours have been,</l>
                  <l>As, in no <hi>former ages,</hi> have been ſeen.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mark</hi> what I <hi>ſay;</hi> and <hi>heed</hi> what will <hi>enſue;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, what I tell you, <hi>is,</hi> and ſhal be true.</l>
                  <l>GOD, for their many <hi>ſins,</hi> did juſtly bring</l>
                  <l>Theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> into <hi>Bondege,</hi> to their <hi>King:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not to deſtroy them, as a <hi>foe,</hi> but rather,</l>
                  <l>Them to correct, as it became a <hi>Father.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That <hi>Pow'r,</hi> He, exerciſ'd not to fulfill</l>
                  <l>GOD's minde, but, to accompliſh his <hi>owne will;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, did exceed the bounds of his <hi>commiſſion,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To make them footſteps, up to his <hi>ambition.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then, unto GOD they cri'd, and did repent;</l>
                  <l>VVho, thereupon, unto their <hi>Parlament</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Gave all his <hi>Power;</hi> whereby, they did proceed</l>
                  <l>Againſt his <hi>life,</hi> and <hi>raigned in his ſteed.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhen they were thus <hi>in-thron'd,</hi> in leiw of <hi>giving,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Forgiving, diſinthralling,</hi> and releiving.</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:116005:28"/>
                  <l>Their <hi>Brethren,</hi> by whoſe hazzards, blood, &amp; treaſure,</l>
                  <l>They, of the <hi>ſov'raigne Power,</hi> had gotten ſeiſure;</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Helpers, Friends,</hi> and <hi>Servants,</hi> they forgot,</l>
                  <l>Or (which is worſe) them, they regarded not;</l>
                  <l>(Nor in their greateſt need, were ſome of thoſe,</l>
                  <l>So civilly reſpected as their <hi>Foes</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Nay more; them they <hi>oppreſt;</hi> ſleighted their <hi>prayers,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Expoſed them to <hi>ſhame, wants,</hi> and <hi>deſpaires;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Endeavour'd chiefly their owne <hi>exaltations,;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Th'inriching of <hi>themſelves,</hi> and their <hi>relations;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, had not that ſucceeded, which befell,</l>
                  <l>What elſe they would have done, no man can tell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In ſight of GOD, of <hi>Angels,</hi> and of <hi>Men,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Theſe things were done; and, this, compels <hi>my pen</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To leave it on <hi>Record,</hi> here to be read</l>
                  <l>By <hi>future Ages,</hi> when that I am dead.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theſe,</hi> and more ſuch like things, which I have been</l>
                  <l>Inforced to have <hi>felt,</hi> and to have <hi>ſeen,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I, from beholding them, long time deſn'd</l>
                  <l>My <hi>ſelf,</hi> into ſome <hi>nook</hi> to have retir'd;</l>
                  <l>But, my <hi>Engagements</hi> alwayes kept me here:</l>
                  <l>Perhaps, that thereof, I might witneſſe bear</l>
                  <l>To glorifie GOD's <hi>Juſtice;</hi> and to ſhow</l>
                  <l>From whence all our <hi>deſtructive changes flow.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And (being that which I ſeem born to do)</l>
                  <l>With willingneſſe, I, now ſubmit thereto,</l>
                  <l>That, to their <hi>Faces,</hi> I may teſtify,</l>
                  <l>What, <hi>thouſands living,</hi> know to be no lye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For theſe <hi>Exorbitances,</hi> (as this day</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e do perceive) GOD, took their <hi>powr</hi> away,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>d gave it to their <hi>Servant,</hi> whom they ſleighted;</l>
                  <l>VVhome, they, perhaps, as ill would have requited,</l>
                  <l>As other men have beene; and, they, are now</l>
                  <l>His <hi>ſervants;</hi> and inforc'd themſelves to bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:116005:29"/>
                  <l>Before his preſence, whom they did contemn,</l>
                  <l>Till, GOD, had with their <hi>power</hi> inveſted him,</l>
                  <l>VVho, is (GOD <hi>ſpeed him well</hi>) on earths wide ſtage,</l>
                  <l>The greateſt <hi>expectation,</hi> of, this age:</l>
                  <l>Yet, at his <hi>Exit,</hi> he, his doome ſhall beare</l>
                  <l>According, as his part, is acted here.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To ev'ry one, of whatſoe'r <hi>Degree,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Such as his <hi>works</hi> are, ſuch, his <hi>meed</hi> ſhall be:</l>
                  <l>And, this, nor <hi>ſtrength,</hi> nor <hi>wiſdome</hi> ſhall prevent;</l>
                  <l>No, not an <hi>Army,</hi> nor a <hi>Parlament,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor long time, ſhall <hi>Prince, Prieſt,</hi> or <hi>People</hi> thrive</l>
                  <l>In any thing, they <hi>hope for,</hi> or <hi>contrive,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But puſſell, plague, and ſtill afflict each other</l>
                  <l>Till they in <hi>Righteous-things</hi> agree together;</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>ſanctifie</hi> this <hi>Commonwealths</hi> foundation</l>
                  <l>With much more <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and with more compaſſion.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I hope, this <hi>downe-right-dealing</hi> (which proceeds</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Conſcience</hi>) no Apologizing needs:</l>
                  <l>But, of their <hi>wrath,</hi> I no whit am afraid</l>
                  <l>To whom, <hi>truth,</hi> may offenſively be ſaid;</l>
                  <l>For, if that any thing thereby befall</l>
                  <l>To me <hi>deſtructive,</hi> much more greive I ſhall</l>
                  <l>For <hi>others</hi> then my <hi>ſelfe;</hi> becauſe, their ends</l>
                  <l>I do foreſee, who ſhall deſtroy their <hi>friends;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, that, if <hi>Juſtice</hi> be not more enjoy'd</l>
                  <l>I, ſhall be <hi>ſafeſt,</hi> when I am deſtroy'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet, <hi>Reader,</hi> pleaſed be before thou goe</l>
                  <l>VVith Candor, to peruſe a few <hi>Lines</hi> moe</l>
                  <l>For my <hi>Indempnity</hi> and, then I've done;</l>
                  <l>Make no <hi>falſe Comments</hi> (prithce) hereupon;</l>
                  <l>Inferre thou not from any word here ſaid,</l>
                  <l>One thought, whereby, <hi>aſperſions</hi> may be laid</l>
                  <l>On that <hi>great Councell,</hi> by whoſe prudence, care,</l>
                  <l>Zeale, pains and love, thoſe things propoſed are</l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:116005:29"/>
                  <l>For his <hi>aſſent,</hi> without whoſe approbation,</l>
                  <l>They cannot have <hi>Authentick Confirmation.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The cauſe is weighty; and, no <hi>Humame eye</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Can all the wayes of <hi>Providence</hi> eſpie.</l>
                  <l>Although their <hi>Offers</hi> are demur'd upon,</l>
                  <l>They, their devoire, as I believe, have done</l>
                  <l>To give advance unto that <hi>Intereſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, in their Judgement, hath appear'd the beſt;</l>
                  <l>And done <hi>Gods worke,</hi> ſo far forth as they could</l>
                  <l>His purpoſes, with <hi>humane eyes</hi> behold;</l>
                  <l>Or, execute his <hi>Will,</hi> by <hi>Reaſons light:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, I do hope, they ſhall (ere that be quite</l>
                  <l>Reſolv'd upon, which yet remains to doe)</l>
                  <l>Receive <hi>Divine Illumination, too.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By that which I have heeded, I conceive</l>
                  <l>(And hold my ſelfe obliged to believe)</l>
                  <l>That, both they, who did on that <hi>Inſtrument</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Agree,</hi> and alſo they, who yet <hi>diſſent,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Their Conſciences, have with an equal Zeale,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>God,</hi> their <hi>Prince,</hi> and to this <hi>Commonweale</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Therein diſcharg'd; and, that thoſe things which bee</l>
                  <l>Well done, are <hi>Beſt done,</hi> when, ſome diſagree:</l>
                  <l>And, that, <hi>Truth</hi> doth appear in her perfection</l>
                  <l>When ſhe is poliſhed by <hi>Contradiction:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>We, therefore, to <hi>both Parties,</hi> owe both <hi>Love</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Civill thanks,</hi> what ere the <hi>Sequels</hi> prove.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Believe me herein; and obſerve, I pray,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>heedfulneſſe,</hi> that which I next ſhall ſay;</l>
                  <l>For, it will much concern us: (and I preſſe</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Caution,</hi> therefore, with ſuch <hi>earneſtneſſe</hi>)</l>
                  <l>When, <hi>that</hi> which was propoſed, once <hi>in vain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(And, which is to be offer'd now again</l>
                  <l>Unto his <hi>Highneſſe</hi>) all debates hath paſt;</l>
                  <l>If then, your <hi>Expectations</hi> fail at laſt</l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:116005:30"/>
                  <l>Which muſt fall out, on th'one or <hi>th'other ſide;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With that, which comes to paſſe, <hi>content abide:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, though in <hi>Judgement,</hi> you devided be;</l>
                  <l>In your <hi>Affections,</hi> loveingly agree.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If they, who their <hi>Propoſals</hi> lately brought,</l>
                  <l>To be allow'd, obtain not what they ſought,</l>
                  <l>Miſcenſure not of them, as if they had</l>
                  <l>With ill <hi>intentions,</hi> thoſe <hi>Propoſals</hi> made;</l>
                  <l>Nor judge amiſſe <hi>of him,</hi> who gave <hi>Deniall;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If, when <hi>repugnant Reaſons</hi> have their <hi>Triall,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He ſhall be ſwayed to conſent, at length,</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Reaſons</hi> of the moſt prevailing ſtrength.</l>
                  <l>For, if his <hi>Highneſſe,</hi> on ſuch tearms <hi>admit</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of that to which he gives <hi>deniall,</hi> yet,</l>
                  <l>As in his <hi>Judgement,</hi> and in <hi>Conſcience</hi> too,</l>
                  <l>Well ſatisfied, in that which he ſhall doe,</l>
                  <l>And hath beforehand, <hi>Gods</hi> direction ſought,</l>
                  <l>(As I believe, he hath done as he ought)</l>
                  <l>Know, it proceeds from <hi>God;</hi> and, that what ere</l>
                  <l>We thereupon think <hi>Probable,</hi> or <hi>Feare,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>We muſt leave <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Him,</hi> to act their part;</l>
                  <l>Not medling with what's hidden in his <hi>heart,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or in an unrevealed <hi>Providence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Leſt, we to both of theſe, give juſt offence;</l>
                  <l>And by prejudicating things unknown,</l>
                  <l>Deſtroy the <hi>Peace</hi> of others, and our own.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When things are done, (for ought that we can know)</l>
                  <l>As, <hi>God,</hi> doth unto him his duty ſhow;</l>
                  <l>If, then, we ſtill <hi>ſuſpect him,</hi> and foment</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>Jealouſies</hi> which nouriſh diſcontent;</l>
                  <l>If we ſhall then imagine his <hi>Delay</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Scruples,</hi> were but onely to make way</l>
                  <l>To new <hi>Deſignes;</hi> or, to accompliſh that</l>
                  <l>Which, we think he hath alwayes aimed at,</l>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:116005:30"/>
                  <l>(Pretending other things, thereby to gain</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Larger Powr</hi> then elſe he ſhould obtain)</l>
                  <l>If we think thus, as I know many do,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe they have been pleas'd to tell me ſo;</l>
                  <l>Then, there will be no remedy or <hi>end</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of what we may <hi>Injuriouſly pretend;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, how oblique ſo e're, his aimes may be,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>We,</hi> make our <hi>ſelves</hi> as culpable as he;</l>
                  <l>And, there is ſomewhat in us, which, no doubt</l>
                  <l>Doth from a <hi>Root of bitterneſſe</hi> ſpring out,</l>
                  <l>That will produce our <hi>Shame;</hi> or, which is worſe,</l>
                  <l>Engage us into ſome <hi>Deſtructive Courſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, if his <hi>heart be right,</hi> ſo much the greater</l>
                  <l>Will our <hi>Shame</hi> be, as his deſignes are better</l>
                  <l>Then we believe they are; and, queſtionleſſe,</l>
                  <l>It will to us contract a <hi>Guiltineſſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That will bring on a <hi>Plague:</hi> and manifeſt</l>
                  <l>That, though againſt <hi>Self-ſeeking</hi> we proteſt;</l>
                  <l>We, have not ſo much prayed, that, <hi>Gods will</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Should take effect, as, our own to fulfill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVhat, of this great <hi>Debate</hi> will be th' <hi>effect,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I know not; nor preſume I to collect</l>
                  <l>From what I know: for, <hi>Princes hearts are deep,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, I, into their <hi>ſecrets</hi> will not peep.</l>
                  <l>VVhen <hi>Abraham,</hi> to ſacrifize his Son</l>
                  <l>Expreſt a <hi>Will,</hi> although it were not <hi>done,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It pleas'd as well; And, GOD, for that proceed,</l>
                  <l>His <hi>willingneſſe,</hi> accepted for the deed.</l>
                  <l>It lies not in our <hi>Actions,</hi> to fulfill</l>
                  <l>VVhat is requir'd, ſo much, as in our will:</l>
                  <l>For, <hi>two men</hi> in <hi>one cauſe</hi> may <hi>fight</hi> (or <hi>grinde</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>At <hi>one Mill,</hi>) yet, but <hi>one,</hi> acceptance finde;</l>
                  <l>And, what to <hi>Act,</hi> the <hi>Law,</hi> on us doth call,</l>
                  <l>Sometimes, by <hi>grace,</hi> may be diſpens'd withall.</l>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:116005:31"/>
                  <l>I, therefore, know not how <hi>inlarge</hi> we may</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>circumſcribe</hi> his <hi>Highneſſe</hi> in his <hi>way;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor how far, GOD, in this <hi>Cauſe,</hi> will allow</l>
                  <l>A diſpenſation after <hi>Tryall</hi> now;</l>
                  <l>Nor which way he will bend his heart at laſt;</l>
                  <l>But, by thoſe things which are already paſt,</l>
                  <l>(And, by ſome other <hi>ſymptomes</hi> which I finde</l>
                  <l>Of many <hi>good performances,</hi> behinde)</l>
                  <l>I hope the beſt: and, ſince no better way</l>
                  <l>I, can be ſerviceable; thus, I <hi>pray.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>On</hi> Earth, <hi>vouchſafe him better things, oh LORD!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then,</hi> Juſtice, <hi>can for</hi> Mans <hi>beſt works afford.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Within the</hi> VVorld <hi>to come, let him inherit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Not that which</hi> He, <hi>but, that, which</hi> Chriſt <hi>doth merit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, give him power before he thither goe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To ſettle</hi> righteouſneſſe <hi>and</hi> mercy <hi>ſo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon his</hi> Throne; <hi>that, they who now condole</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>May ſing a bleſſed</hi> Requiem <hi>to his ſoul;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, that their</hi> hopes <hi>deferd, may be injoyd,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Before,</hi> they, <hi>or their</hi> patience, <hi>are deſtroyd.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our <hi>God,</hi> hath many wayes to bring about</l>
                  <l>What he hath foreintended to work out.</l>
                  <l>That, which <hi>Conditionally</hi> to be done</l>
                  <l>He <hi>Wils,</hi> muſt take effect in every one</l>
                  <l>As thoſe <hi>Conditions</hi> are performd by <hi>them,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To whom, his <hi>Offers</hi> are propos'd by <hi>him;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, that which he hath <hi>abſolutely Willd,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall doubtleſſe, <hi>abſolutely be fulfil'd,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What ever <hi>Contrarieties,</hi> here, ſhall</l>
                  <l>Thereto obſtructive, ſeemingly befall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For <hi>my part,</hi> therefore, when the <hi>Trial's</hi> ended,</l>
                  <l>Which, I unfeighnedly have recommended</l>
                  <l>To <hi>God,</hi> my <hi>Prince,</hi> and <hi>Country;</hi> I'le rejoyce</l>
                  <l>More in <hi>their chuſing,</hi> then, in mine <hi>owne choyce.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:116005:31"/>
                  <l>Although I ſuffer by it; with beleefe,</l>
                  <l>It will, at laſt, produce more <hi>joy,</hi> then <hi>greife.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In that <hi>Ship,</hi> which the <hi>common Fraight</hi> doth beare,</l>
                  <l>I, am but onely a poore <hi>Paſſenger,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who, moved thereto by an honeſt zeale,</l>
                  <l>Have ſpoken, what I thought concernd her weale;</l>
                  <l>And, though I have hereby inſiſted much</l>
                  <l>On my <hi>owne ſenſe;</hi> and think it to bee ſuch</l>
                  <l>As may bee own'd; Though, ſuch it be reputed</l>
                  <l>By <hi>others,</hi> and ſhall never be refuted;</l>
                  <l>Yea, though, I may diſcover ſome things done,</l>
                  <l>By which, my <hi>juſt rights</hi> are intrenchd upon;</l>
                  <l>Yet (having done my duty) I will beare</l>
                  <l>Thoſe things with patience, which concluded are;</l>
                  <l>And, not alone ſubmit, to what they doe,</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Goods</hi> and <hi>Perſon,</hi> but, my <hi>Reaſon</hi> too:</l>
                  <l>At leaſt ſo farr forth, that, I will not preſſe</l>
                  <l>One <hi>Argument,</hi> by which the <hi>common-peace</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May be indangerd; but, do what I may</l>
                  <l>To ſerve my <hi>Country</hi> in a <hi>ſober way:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>ſilence,</hi> things which are amiſſe deplore;</l>
                  <l>Think my own <hi>ſinnes</hi> deſerved that, and more;</l>
                  <l>Mark my <hi>own failings;</hi> and perſwaded be</l>
                  <l>Theſe things have happend, to make proofe of <hi>me,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſuch, as I, as well, as proofe to make</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>thoſe</hi> who were engaged for our ſake:</l>
                  <l>And, praiſe <hi>God,</hi> though all things be not ſo well</l>
                  <l>As I <hi>deſire,</hi> that, nothing worſe befell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, from thoſe <hi>difficulties</hi> and <hi>confuſions,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which we are in, to draw forth ſuch <hi>concluſions</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As may not be gainſayd, in ſome repſect,</l>
                  <l>Is more then <hi>Human wiſdome</hi> can effect.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Courſe</hi> by which we purpoſe to perſue</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beloved Peace,</hi> loathd <hi>Diſcords</hi> may renew;</l>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:116005:32"/>
                  <l>And, whilſt we fighting are, from <hi>Foes</hi> to clear</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Vann,</hi> we may be routed in the <hi>Rear.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By thoſe <hi>Contrivements,</hi> whereby, we ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>To ſave our <hi>Lives,</hi> our <hi>Honors</hi> we may loſe.</l>
                  <l>By that, through which our <hi>Perſons</hi> might be free,</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Conſciences,</hi> perhaps, inſlav'd may be;</l>
                  <l>And, what, for <hi>preſent ſafety,</hi> we endeavour,</l>
                  <l>May for the <hi>future,</hi> ruine us for ever.</l>
                  <l>So <hi>finite</hi> is our <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> and our <hi>Powr,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, thoſe things which may <hi>weaken</hi> or <hi>devour,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So <hi>infinite;</hi> that, we as well may ſpan</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Firmament,</hi> as, by the wit of <hi>Man</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Contrive, or ſettle ſuch a <hi>Government,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As will our dangers every way prevent.</l>
                  <l>For, that which is <hi>beſt done,</hi> and <hi>beſt intended,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Will ſtill have ſomewhat in it to be mended:</l>
                  <l>Yea, even the <hi>beſt things,</hi> which <hi>beſt men</hi> can doe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Inſnarings</hi> have injected thereinto,</l>
                  <l>To catch <hi>themſelves,</hi> or <hi>others;</hi> which, none ſcapes</l>
                  <l>But, he, that alwayes <hi>lookes</hi> before he <hi>leapes;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſeekes for <hi>Councell</hi> and <hi>Protection,</hi> from</l>
                  <l>That <hi>ſaving-powr,</hi> whence all our <hi>ſafeties</hi> come.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He therefore is injurious, who ſuſpects</l>
                  <l>All deeds <hi>ill purpoſ'd,</hi> which have ill <hi>effects;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, who, thoſe Mens <hi>Faiths</hi> into queſtion cals,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe <hi>Councell</hi> under ſome Aſperſion fals:</l>
                  <l>No leſſe unjuſt are they, who froward be</l>
                  <l>Becauſe, he takes his <hi>freedome</hi> who is <hi>free,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet, takes thereof no more then doth belong</l>
                  <l>Unto <hi>himſelfe,</hi> without his <hi>Neighbours wrong:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, they, are not in every poynt ſo wiſe</l>
                  <l>As they might be, who, <hi>good advice</hi> deſpiſe</l>
                  <l>(And timely ay'd, when they are like to ſuffer)</l>
                  <l>Becauſe, that man, whom <hi>conſcience</hi> mooves to offer</l>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:116005:32"/>
                  <l>His <hi>ſervices;</hi> within the <hi>Camp,</hi> hath hid</l>
                  <l>Himſelf, as <hi>Eldad,</hi> and as <hi>Medad</hi> did.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe things conſiderd, I, perſwaded am</l>
                  <l>That neither I, nor any merits blame,</l>
                  <l>For ought <hi>well propos'd:</hi> and, that now the day</l>
                  <l>Is near at hand, which will prepare <hi>a way</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To what <hi>Good men</hi> deſire: and, that a deed,</l>
                  <l>Which did from <hi>Conſcientiouſneſs</hi> proceed.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> no bar ſhall prove,</l>
                  <l>To that which may our <hi>Grievances</hi> remove.</l>
                  <l>In this <hi>hope,</hi> I with <hi>patience</hi> do attend</l>
                  <l>What <hi>God will</hi> do; to whom, I recommend</l>
                  <l>The perfecting, of what men <hi>ſtrive</hi> about,</l>
                  <l>For, <hi>hee</hi> muſt do it. Now, this <hi>Flaſh</hi> is out.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A SPARK.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BUt ſee, here's of that <hi>Flaſh,</hi> a little <hi>Spark</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet unextinguiſh'd; which, I pray you mark.</l>
                  <l>My <hi>lifes</hi> tenth <hi>Clymax</hi> is now ſpent well near,</l>
                  <l>And yet, my <hi>warfare</hi> is unfiniſh'd here.</l>
                  <l>I therefore, by this <hi>Flaſh</hi> a triall make,</l>
                  <l>How, if need be, <hi>Old Powder,</hi> fire will take;</l>
                  <l>That when occaſion calls mee ſo to do,</l>
                  <l>I, therewith might diſcharge a <hi>ſhot</hi> or <hi>two,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or light a <hi>Beacon,</hi> timely to <hi>Alarm</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thoſe, who may by <hi>ſurprizall,</hi> ſuffer harm;</l>
                  <l>And ſave that, by th' <hi>Artillery</hi> of <hi>words,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, cannot be ſecur'd by <hi>Guns</hi> and <hi>Swords.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, though by <hi>age,</hi> my <hi>Arms,</hi> are uſeleſs found,</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Heart</hi> ſo ſtrong remains, my <hi>Brain</hi> ſo ſound,</l>
                  <l>That both by <hi>Action,</hi> and by <hi>Contemplation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I may, yet, ſome way ſerve this <hi>Generations;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:116005:33"/>
                  <l>Whoſe <hi>Welfare</hi> to promote, I have beſtown,</l>
                  <l>More time and coſt, then to advance mine <hi>own.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, when my <hi>heart's</hi> broke, &amp; hath crack't my <hi>brain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When all thoſe <hi>helps,</hi> which unto <hi>life</hi> pertain;</l>
                  <l>When all the <hi>preſent hopes</hi> of things <hi>without me,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Which to and fro, do <hi>flutter</hi> yet about me)</l>
                  <l>Are flown away; (as daily 'tis expected)</l>
                  <l>Then, will to mind be brought, <hi>things now neglected:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>that</hi> be done, which, yet, <hi>ſelf-love</hi> and <hi>pride</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Obſtruct; and will, till they be <hi>laid aſide.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yea, then, with <hi>good reſpect,</hi> that will be heard,</l>
                  <l>Which, at this preſent, hath but ſmall <hi>regard.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Mean-while, I reſt contented with my <hi>Lot;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, I have that <hi>eſteem</hi> which others got</l>
                  <l>In <hi>former times,</hi> who did <hi>this way,</hi> declare</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>Notions,</hi> wherewithall inſpir'd they were;</l>
                  <l>And, to diſcharge my duties, am a debter,</l>
                  <l>Though my requitall, never ſhould be better.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There lies a little <hi>Grain,</hi> rack'd up within,</l>
                  <l>From whence, my <hi>better-being</hi> will begin:</l>
                  <l>And, when moſt <hi>Weakneſſes</hi> appear in me,</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Powr,</hi> ſhall then, in <hi>full-perfection</hi> be:</l>
                  <l>Yea, when I have nor <hi>Life, Fleſh, Blood,</hi> nor <hi>Bone,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then, that, which could not by thoſe <hi>Tools</hi> be done,</l>
                  <l>Shall be performd; and, many things which are</l>
                  <l>Yet <hi>dark,</hi> will <hi>plain,</hi> and uſefull, then, appear.</l>
                  <l>Mean-while, O <hi>God</hi> vouchſafe thou, to <hi>forgive</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What, hinders their <hi>performance,</hi> whil'ſt I <hi>live.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <closer>So prays,
<signed>Britans Remembrancer.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="addendum">
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:116005:33"/>
            <head>A Cauſe Allegorically Stated,</head>
            <head type="sub">With an <hi>Appeal</hi> therein, to all that are <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>honeſt,</hi> from an injurious <hi>cenſure,</hi> lately paſſed.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>A <hi>Goodly Ship,</hi> with precious lading fraught,</l>
               <l>Late, in a <hi>dark night,</hi> near to <hi>land</hi> was brought.</l>
               <l>Through many <hi>dangers,</hi> and much <hi>Bluſtering weather,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Providence of God,</hi> had brought her thither;</l>
               <l>And, by the <hi>Waters motions,</hi> and ſome <hi>Humming</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Among the <hi>Shrowds,</hi> another <hi>ſtorm</hi> ſeem'd coming.</l>
               <l>The <hi>place ariv'd at,</hi> was a dangerous <hi>Bay,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From which, into the <hi>Port,</hi> two <hi>Channells</hi> lay,</l>
               <l>Divided by a <hi>Quicksand,</hi> with great ſtore</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Shelvs,</hi> and <hi>Sharp-rocks,</hi> upon either <hi>Shore:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>She had a brave <hi>Commander, Marchants</hi> many;</l>
               <l>Stout <hi>Seamen, Pilots</hi> too, as good as any,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Paſſengers</hi> of all ſorts; among whom</l>
               <l>Some could (had need been) have ſuppli'd the room</l>
               <l>Of <hi>well experiens'd Sea-men,</hi> and advis'd</l>
               <l>Such things, as <hi>Prudence</hi> would not have diſpis'd.</l>
               <l>But, theſe among themſelvs, divided were,</l>
               <l>Through which of theſe two <hi>Channels,</hi> they ſhould ſteer,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>One party,</hi> thinking that the <hi>ſafeſt way,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In which the <hi>other,</hi> thought moſt <hi>danger</hi> lay:</l>
               <l>And in the <hi>dark,</hi> it could not well be ſeen,</l>
               <l>In which, the greateſt <hi>Hazzard</hi> would have been.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There was a poor <hi>Old man,</hi> that time, a board,</l>
               <l>To whom, <hi>God,</hi> had been pleaſed to afford</l>
               <l>A <hi>faculty,</hi> to ſee things in the <hi>dark,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which others could not <hi>view,</hi> or, did not <hi>mark;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He, ſeeing what great <hi>ſtraights</hi> the <hi>Ship</hi> was in,</l>
               <l>And what their loſs was likely to have been,</l>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:116005:34"/>
               <l>Call'd out to thoſe, who there had <hi>Chief Commmand;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſaid; <hi>there</hi> ſtands a <hi>Rock;</hi> here lies a <hi>ſand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Another <hi>yonder,</hi> and, a <hi>Whirlpool</hi> there;</l>
               <l>Be carefull therefore, <hi>thither not to ſteer;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bear</hi> up a little while into the <hi>Wind,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Although a ſhew of danger there you find)</l>
               <l>And take heed, that a cauſleſs fear or doubt,</l>
               <l>Prevails not now, to make you <hi>Tack-about:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Leſt all be loſt, and, you, upon a <hi>ſteep</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ridge ſtrike;</hi> and, <hi>over-ſet</hi> into the <hi>deep.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now, by the <hi>Starbordſide</hi> a compaſs fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch,</l>
               <l>Halfe way to <hi>you point,</hi> to avoyd <hi>that Beach;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And then, upon the <hi>Larbordſide</hi> again</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wheel off,</hi> and you the <hi>Harbor</hi> ſhall attain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus ſpake the <hi>Old man:</hi> for although 'twere night,</l>
               <l>He ſaw as well, as when the <hi>Sun</hi> gives light;</l>
               <l>And then, all they who had a will to ſee,</l>
               <l>Saw how to find the <hi>way,</hi> as well as hee.</l>
               <l>The <hi>greater part,</hi> not heeding what they heard,</l>
               <l>(Nor knowing their own danger) <hi>grinn'd</hi> and <hi>jeer'd;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Suppos'd him mad, to talk, and make a ſhew</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Demonſtrations,</hi> which they could not view;</l>
               <l>Crept from the <hi>hatches,</hi> down into the <hi>hold,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And let them look unto the <hi>Ship</hi> that would.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But, they, who more ſought their own <hi>will</hi> to have,</l>
               <l>Then to be <hi>counſel'd,</hi> or, the <hi>Ship</hi> to ſave;</l>
               <l>Diſdaining that an aged <hi>doting fool,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Should put their <hi>Wiſedom,</hi> as it were, to ſchool;</l>
               <l>(And, ſeeing his <hi>Relations</hi> tend unto,</l>
               <l>That, which their <hi>Captain</hi> had reſolv'd to do)</l>
               <l>Grew <hi>angry,</hi> Therefore, though he neither fears</l>
               <l>Their <hi>wrath,</hi> nor much for their <hi>disfavour</hi> cares;</l>
               <l>Hereby, he hath appealed unto you,</l>
               <l>Who, are known <hi>honeſt, wiſe, goodmen,</hi> and true;</l>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:116005:34"/>
               <l>And, praies you, to be Judges, how he hath,</l>
               <l>Or wherein, any way deſerv'd their <hi>Wrath:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For, here in brief, his <hi>Cauſe</hi> is plainly ſhow'n,</l>
               <l>And, 'tis to ſome among you, ſo well known,</l>
               <l>That, if you ſhall condemne him, hee'l ſubmit</l>
               <l>To make what <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> you think fit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>If this comes forth too late to take effect,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My <hi>Conſcience</hi> knows, it was not my neglect:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For I, my utmoſt <hi>labour,</hi> had beſtown,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To make it, in <hi>a timely-ſeaſon</hi> known.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If, therefore, ought amiſſe thereby enſue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>There lay the <hi>Fault,</hi> to whom the <hi>Blame</hi> is due.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="addendum">
            <pb facs="tcp:116005:35"/>
            <head>Here being vacant <hi>Pages,</hi> the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> hath filled them with a Copie of certain <hi>Verſes,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he lately incloſed two <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions</hi> to the PARLAMENT, and laid them within their <hi>Threſhold;</hi> hoping by that <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient,</hi> they might have been preſented to the <hi>Houſe;</hi> The Paper was thus Superſcribed; <q>To that <hi>Member</hi> of <hi>PARLAMENT,</hi> who takes up this <hi>Paper,</hi> with the <hi>Petition</hi> incloſed.</q>
            </head>
            <p>The Verſes are theſe:</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, if you are not of this PARLAMENT,</l>
               <l>Herewith to greet you, 'tis not my intent;</l>
               <l>But, if a <hi>Member</hi> of this <hi>Houſe</hi> you are,</l>
               <l>Your taking up this <hi>Paper</hi> (as it were)</l>
               <l>By <hi>Lot,</hi> ingageth you to manage thoſe</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Petitions,</hi> which, therewith I did incloſe,</l>
               <l>As, you would have <hi>another,</hi> uſe his pow'r,</l>
               <l>Therein, for <hi>your avail,</hi> were my <hi>caſe</hi> your:</l>
               <l>Whereof take this <hi>Account;</hi> and, why I play</l>
               <l>My Cards refus'd, in this <hi>unuſual way.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:116005:35"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Three Parlaments</hi> (the eldeſt of which <hi>three,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Might, had it pleaſed our LORD, have out-liv'd me)</l>
               <l>Are dead and gone, ſince firſt I did complain</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Grievances,</hi> which hitherto remain</l>
               <l>Without <hi>Redreſs.</hi> I, alſo have ſurviv'd</l>
               <l>To ſee a <hi>Fourth,</hi> which hath it ſelf out-liv'd,</l>
               <l>And may continue, till it hath ſuppli'd</l>
               <l>What, <hi>Providence,</hi> is thereby to provide</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For needful <hi>ſupplements,</hi> to carry on</l>
               <l>Thoſe <hi>Works,</hi> which in theſe <hi>Nations</hi> are begun.</l>
               <l>God grant it <hi>Pow'r,</hi> and <hi>Will,</hi> and <hi>Time,</hi> to do</l>
               <l>What, they by <hi>Duty,</hi> are oblig'd unto,</l>
               <l>That, they from <hi>wrongs,</hi> the <hi>wronged</hi> may releaſe;</l>
               <l>Proceed with <hi>Honour,</hi> and conclude in <hi>Peace.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To ſuch <hi>Atchievments,</hi> there's a <hi>middle-way,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Twixt <hi>This,</hi> and <hi>That;</hi> 'twixt <hi>haſt,</hi> and <hi>long-delay:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which, if <hi>miſtaken,</hi> or not <hi>timely found,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>May (as it hath done) lead into a <hi>Round,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Or <hi>Labyrinth</hi>) whereby, we may be brought</l>
               <l>To <hi>pits</hi> and <hi>ſnares,</hi> which have no <hi>paſſage out;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And multiply <hi>diſtractions,</hi> till our <hi>prai'rs</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Are turn'd to <hi>indignation,</hi> or <hi>diſpairs:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which, is their <hi>drift</hi> (and not their leaſt <hi>deſigne</hi>)</l>
               <l>Who, ſeek this <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> to undermine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>publick wants,</hi> require to be ſuppl'd,</l>
               <l>A <hi>private plaint</hi> may then be laid aſide,</l>
               <l>But, not too long deferr'd, leſt it become</l>
               <l>A <hi>feſtring-ſoar,</hi> not meanly perilſome:</l>
               <l>For, ſince an <hi>Univerſal-weal</hi> conſiſts</l>
               <l>Of many <hi>Individual Intereſts,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A <hi>perfect Body</hi> cannot be injoi'd,</l>
               <l>Where, <hi>One</hi> by <hi>One,</hi> the <hi>Members</hi> are deſtroi'd;</l>
               <l>And, when the <hi>Eie</hi> or <hi>Ear,</hi> unheedful grows</l>
               <l>Of what, afflicts the <hi>fingers,</hi> and the <hi>Toes;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:116005:36"/>
               <l>Much leſſe, when it neglects what appertains</l>
               <l>To keep it, from an <hi>Ulcer</hi> in the <hi>Brains.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>cures</hi> therefore, of <hi>private wants,</hi> betwixt</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Publick tranſactions,</hi> ſhould be intermixt;</l>
               <l>(At leaſt ſomtimes) in thoſe <hi>immergent things,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wherein, delay of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> loſſes brings</l>
               <l>Beyond repair; or where the <hi>State</hi> at laſt</l>
               <l>Muſt bear the <hi>dammage,</hi> when the <hi>cure</hi> is paſt;</l>
               <l>Or elſe, in <hi>point of honour,</hi> ſuffer more</l>
               <l>Then all the <hi>publick treaſure</hi> will reſtore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I grudg not, when GOD's <hi>glory</hi> is at ſtake,</l>
               <l>That they, who conſcience of their <hi>Votes</hi> do make,</l>
               <l>Should take the <hi>freedom</hi> to debate at large,</l>
               <l>What, may their <hi>duties</hi> in their place diſcharge;</l>
               <l>Or, when the <hi>Common-ſafety</hi> doth appear</l>
               <l>In hazard, though my life in danger were:</l>
               <l>But, when thoſe <hi>brunts</hi> are over, if men pleaſe,</l>
               <l>For their meer <hi>pleaſure, profit,</hi> or their <hi>eaſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To leave us in a periſhing condition,</l>
               <l>It, of their <hi>faithfulneſs,</hi> may give ſuſpition;</l>
               <l>And, I more grieve, for what I thereby ſee</l>
               <l>May on the <hi>publick fall,</hi> then <hi>falls</hi> on <hi>mee.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There's <hi>time</hi> enough in all <hi>ſtreights</hi> whatſoe're,</l>
               <l>For all things, if it well divided were:</l>
               <l>And, for our not apportioning aright</l>
               <l>The <hi>time</hi> we have (as <hi>wiſemen</hi> ſee we might)</l>
               <l>GOD, cuts off half the daies we ſhould have had,</l>
               <l>And our <hi>deſignments</hi> are abortive made.</l>
               <l>As wee from <hi>week</hi> to <hi>week,</hi> from <hi>day</hi> to <hi>day</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Do put off thoſe, who for our ſuccours pray;</l>
               <l>So likewiſe, are our <hi>ſuits</hi> and <hi>hopes</hi> put by,</l>
               <l>By <hi>him,</hi> on whoſe aſſiſtance we rely.</l>
               <l>An <hi>hour</hi> therefore, ſhould otherwhile be ſpent,</l>
               <l>To give <hi>Reward,</hi> as well as <hi>Puniſhment;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:116005:36"/>
               <l>To think on them who help us in our <hi>ſorrow;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As well to make <hi>repaiments,</hi> as to <hi>borrow;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And, like the <hi>Tree</hi> that's planted by a <hi>ſpring,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Expected <hi>fruits,</hi> in <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> we ſhould bring;</l>
               <l>Not nine or ten years after they are dead,</l>
               <l>(Who, by our <hi>timely fruit</hi> ſhould have been ſed)</l>
               <l>Leſt we be felled by the <hi>Wood-mans</hi> hand,</l>
               <l>Or, like the <hi>Fig-tree,</hi> wither where we ſtand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>One day,</hi> is as well ſpar'd ſometime, to ſave</l>
               <l>An <hi>honeſt-man,</hi> as <hi>nine</hi> to doom a <hi>knave;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And, of an <hi>uſeful Plant</hi> to take due care,</l>
               <l>As, from the <hi>good-corn,</hi> to weed out a <hi>Tare.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Some private <hi>acts of Juſtice,</hi> with our <hi>zeal</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To <hi>Piety,</hi> and to the <hi>Publick-weal,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Or <hi>works of mercy</hi>) ſprinkled here and there</l>
               <l>Among them, like <hi>embroid'ries</hi> would appear,</l>
               <l>Or flowers of gold and ſilver <hi>interwove,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And helpful be, <hi>devotion</hi> to improve:</l>
               <l>For, where few <hi>private grievances</hi> are heard,</l>
               <l>God, gives their <hi>publick praiers</hi> ſmall regard:</l>
               <l>And, few are in that <hi>Common-wealth</hi> much joi'd,</l>
               <l>By which, their own <hi>well-being</hi> is deſtroi'd;</l>
               <l>Or, which is ſenſleſs, of their ſad eſtate,</l>
               <l>Who did help ſave it, from a <hi>ſadder fate.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Among ſuch <hi>ſuff'rers,</hi> I my ſelf am <hi>One,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who, gladly would be better thought upon,</l>
               <l>For your own ſakes; who, peradventure, may</l>
               <l>Have by my <hi>loſſe,</hi> twice mine, another way.</l>
               <l>As many <hi>years</hi> as are equivalent</l>
               <l>To <hi>two men's lives,</hi> I have already ſpent</l>
               <l>To ſeek for <hi>Juſtice,</hi> with ſuch <hi>coſt,</hi> ſuch <hi>trouble,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>loſſe of time,</hi> as make my loſſes double:</l>
               <l>So that if many <hi>ſuits,</hi> here, at this rate,</l>
               <l>I had depending, <hi>three times my eſtate,</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:116005:37"/>
               <l>And <hi>three mens lives,</hi> would ſcarce afford me <hi>time,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>means</hi> enough, whereby to finiſh them:</l>
               <l>For, my <hi>Petitions,</hi> either were deferr'd</l>
               <l>From <hi>mouth</hi> to <hi>mouth,</hi> from <hi>year</hi> to <hi>year,</hi> unheard,</l>
               <l>Or anſwer'd ſo, that when my <hi>ſuit</hi> ſeemd, done,</l>
               <l>My <hi>Caſe</hi> prov'd worſe, then when it firſt begun;</l>
               <l>And, to obſtruct the <hi>Juſtice</hi> I emplore,</l>
               <l>They, voice me to be <hi>rich,</hi> who make me <hi>poor.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With <hi>mock-ſhews</hi> of relief, I have been fed;</l>
               <l>With <hi>ſtones,</hi> In my <hi>diſtreſs,</hi> inſtead of <hi>bread;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which, had ere this day ſtarv'd me, but that GOD,</l>
               <l>Turns many of them, into <hi>wholſome food;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And rais'd me a <hi>ſubſiſtance,</hi> out of that</l>
               <l>Which was deſign'd to ruine my <hi>eſtate.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His <hi>Highneſs,</hi> alſo ſtor'd me with a <hi>Diſh,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which hath converted <hi>Scorpions,</hi> into <hi>Fiſh:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Elſe, that <hi>ſmall portion,</hi> which I yet poſſeſſe,</l>
               <l>(And ſome Envie) had long ago been leſſe,</l>
               <l>(It may be <hi>nothing</hi>); for, that <hi>Act of Grace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is made leſſe valuable, then it was</l>
               <l>By him intended, of whoſe free donation</l>
               <l>It was conferr'd, beyond my expectation.</l>
               <l>Oh! if that I, who have ſome <hi>friends,</hi> thus far'd,</l>
               <l>How ſpeed poor men, whom no man doth regard?</l>
               <l>And, who, from none, can claime an obligation,</l>
               <l>Either by <hi>Friendſhip, Faction,</hi> or <hi>Relation?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But, now, <hi>new-miſadventures</hi> me beſet,</l>
               <l>Which, by delay of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> do beget</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Increaſing miſchiefs,</hi> that admit no <hi>cure,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Save, what muſt from a <hi>Legiſlative pow'r,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Derived be: And, this befalls me ſo,</l>
               <l>Perhaps, that I, in every <hi>Change,</hi> may know,</l>
               <l>The <hi>gen'ral temper,</hi> by the <hi>pulſe</hi> that beats</l>
               <l>Both in Superiour, and Inferiour ſeats;</l>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:116005:37"/>
               <l>That, I, thereby may calculate the length</l>
               <l>Of our <hi>oppreſſions,</hi> and improve my ſtrenth</l>
               <l>To bear them: mark, how well our <hi>publick Acts,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ingagements, Orders, Bargains,</hi> and <hi>Contracts</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Will be perform'd; and, that, as by <hi>preſage,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of things that ſince befell, I told this <hi>Age</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Before they came; ſo, I, might likewiſe tell</l>
               <l>The <hi>next Age,</hi> what I ſaw <hi>done ill,</hi> or <hi>well.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> many have beſought to entertain,</l>
               <l>And offer my petitions, but, in vain.</l>
               <l>Now therefore, having with ſome patience ſtayd</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Six months</hi> at door, to get my <hi>ſuites</hi> convayd</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto this <hi>Houſe,</hi> where, ſeeing ev'ry day,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>New ſuitors</hi> more and more ſtop up the way,</l>
               <l>And ſmall ſigne, that, with any I ſhould meet,</l>
               <l>To <hi>hand them in,</hi> I laid them at their <hi>feet</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who paſs in thither; hopeful, that it may,</l>
               <l>For my <hi>inclos</hi>'d <hi>Petitions</hi> make <hi>free way,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Through thoſe <hi>Obstructions,</hi> which have ſhut the <hi>gate</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Againſt them, till they come almoſt too late.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>He,</hi> who ſhall <hi>take them up,</hi> and get them read,</l>
               <l>Where, with effect, they may be anſwered;</l>
               <l>A <hi>Favour</hi> ſhall confer, by doing ſo,</l>
               <l>On <hi>me,</hi> and likewiſe upon <hi>many moe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For, if my <hi>ſuits,</hi> obtain reſpective heed,</l>
               <l>Some other men, wil hope, as well to ſpeed;</l>
               <l>And of my <hi>wrongs,</hi> if no redreſs I have,</l>
               <l>Both I, and they much future coſt may ſave.</l>
               <l>GOD ſpeed it well: for, I, with what event</l>
               <l>He gives it, am reſolv'd, to be content;</l>
               <l>And, am aſſur'd, that though I be neglected,</l>
               <l>By <hi>men,</hi> I ſhall of him, be <hi>ſtill reſpected.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Britans Remembrancer.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:116005:38"/>
            <head>A <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> to the Preceding <hi>Verſes.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>THey, who to neither <hi>Side,</hi> nor <hi>Back,</hi> nor <hi>Further</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Can <hi>turn,</hi> or <hi>paſs,</hi> need no <hi>Reſtraints</hi> by <hi>Order.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor greatly be afraid what next will come,</l>
               <l>Their, juſt <hi>reſolvings,</hi> to divert them from;</l>
               <l>And, that, whereto <hi>neceſſities</hi> compell,</l>
               <l>Is <hi>done excuſably,</hi> though not <hi>done well.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If much <hi>oppreſſion,</hi> cracks a <hi>wiſeman's</hi> brain,</l>
               <l>Who knows, whereto, it may a <hi>fool</hi> conſtrain?</l>
               <l>They, whom <hi>delay of Juſtice</hi> doth make <hi>poor,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Do loſe but their <hi>eſtates,</hi> and, may get more:</l>
               <l>If, therewithall, they are of life depriv'd,</l>
               <l>They <hi>feel</hi> not, what to <hi>feel,</hi> they might have <hi>liv'd:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But, he who doth in <hi>life-time,</hi> thereby loſe</l>
               <l>Both <hi>wealth</hi> and <hi>credit,</hi> ſhall to <hi>friends</hi> and <hi>foes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Become a <hi>ſcorn;</hi> whereat, if <hi>mad</hi> he be,</l>
               <l>And, makes <hi>ten thouſands</hi> grow as mad as he,</l>
               <l>The <hi>fault</hi> is theirs, who, without mercy, ſtretch</l>
               <l>A weak man's <hi>patience,</hi> farther then 'twil reach;</l>
               <l>As if, he, of his <hi>ſuff'ring</hi> ſenſe had none,</l>
               <l>Becauſe, they no more feel it, then a <hi>ſtone.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My <hi>principle</hi> (which makes me oft abus'd)</l>
               <l>Injoins me, when I ſcurvily am us'd</l>
               <l>Where I expect <hi>relief,</hi> to ſhew my <hi>wrongs;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And, <hi>vengeance</hi> leave, to whom the ſame belongs;</l>
               <l>But, <hi>ſome men,</hi> cannot be content to ſtay</l>
               <l>GOD's leiſure, or, for <hi>Juſtice,</hi> in his <hi>way;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And, what, their <hi>wants, neglects,</hi> and <hi>indignation</hi>
               </l>
               <l>May tempt them to, is worth conſideration.</l>
               <l>There is to all things, an appointed <hi>date;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And, they are <hi>unwiſe,</hi> who are <hi>wiſe too late.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <l>
               <hi>Neceſſitas, &amp; indignatio quid non poſſunt</hi>
            </l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:116005:38"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
